Alright let's get started with colab notebook
this first video's gonna be
review of numpy which is a framework of working with matrices and multi dimensional arrays
If you feel like you already know numpy pretty well
이 리뷰가 정말 필요합니다. 파이 토치
you don't really need this review feel free to skip with next video we started talking about pytorch
Okay, so overview of numpy
행렬을 저장하고 조작하는 객체
numpy arrays are basically objects that you store and manipulate matrices
so here we're gonna define three different numpy arrays
다른 모양에는
each with different shapes
We have one dimensional one
3차원 배열
We have two dimensional array and then we have three dimensional array
하여 값이 어떻게
so let's print all this out
기본적으로 각 방향에서 각각의 목록 길이를 정의하는 모양이라고 합니다.
and we can see how their values are represented
and we can also see that there is a probably called shape
that defines basically the length of list in each direction
so here we have a shape six one dimensional vector
and we have 2 by 3 matrix and then we have a 3 by 2 by three multi dimensional array
some of you know how to use python list you can use integers or slices
so you can index into numpy arrays
similar to how you would with python list you can use integers or slices
but additionally you can specify indices for multiple dimensions of the array
so this example we're gonna create an array that has shape four by five
1에서 20까지의 모든 값을 갖
습니다.
and it's gonna have all the values from one to twenty
so let's print this out first and you can see the values here
and let's start by maybe indexing to a single value of the array
that would be row 2 of the array so I should get the numbers 11 through 15.
that's what I see here
we can also provide indices for multiple dimensions
so let's say I want row 2 column 3 of the array I want the number 14
so I should do 2 comma 3 and that's what I would get here
그것이 내가 여기에서 얻을 수 있는 것입니다.
and finally you can also do a combination of integer indices and slices
just like you do it with python list
so here what I'm doing is I'm getting all the rows from two onwards
and for each of those rows I'm gonna get the value in the third column
so that would give me these two rows third values of 14 and 19.
In numpy you can do all sorts like arithmetic on numpy arrays as long as their dimensions match
so in this example let's try adding these two arrays that are 2 by 3
and it's basically going to add the numbers element wise
and sometimes you can also do these arithmetic operations on arrays
whose dimentions don't exactly match
할 수도 있습니다.  배열 중 하나에 값이 충분하지 않습니다
because basically when you don't have enough values in one of the arrays
the values will kind of be stretched or copied so that their dimensions do match
so it's probably the easiest we look at an example here
음, 하나의 숫자 3이 있다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
so let's say we have a single number three and then we have 2 by 3 matrix
기본적으로 이것이
we can multiply that single number by the matrix and what's going to do is
숫자 3에 이러한 각 요소를
basically pretend that this was a matrix that was 2 by 3 and multiply the number 3 by each of these elements
배열 1 2 3이
and similarly let's say we have an array 1, 2, 3
and then we have this z matrix
기본적으로 숫자
which we defined earlier to be shape 3 by 2 by 3
여기에서 최종 결과를 얻기 위해 이러한 행을 사용
and you can still add these together because it'lll basically copy the number 1, 2, 3
and add it to each of these rows to get this final result here
so this is called broadcasting when you have two arrays that aren't quite the same shape
but you can still add them together or do other operations to combine them
and there are a lot of benefits of doing it this way as opposed to explicitly defining
to numpy arrays that have the exact same shape
은 정확히 동일한 모양을 가진 두 개의 numpy 배열을 명시적으로 정의하는 것과는 대조적
first code is more concise
like in this example we didn't have to create an array that just had the number three duplicated six times
and also you don't have to actually store those duplicated values you don't explicitly create them or store them in a memory
하지 않는 복제된 값을 실제로 저장할
and there are some optimizations happening under the hood and numpy that makes these operations run faster if you do them through broadcasting
so it's nice both for consciseness and for performance benefits
되도록 하는 후드와 numpy 아래에서 발생하는 몇 가지 최적화
for the most part the way that broadcasting works is pretty intuitive like
like it kind of duplicates the value exactly like you'd expect
과 성능상의 이점
방송이 작동하는 방식은 예상
but sometimes you might end up working on something a little more complicated
and if there is ever any doubt about how boradcasting works
I highly encourage you to check out this link over here and that gives a pretty nice short summary of
how exactly the shapes are working out
so next there is an important concept in numpy called axes
numpy라는 축
axes and numpy arrays are basically like the directions along which you can do certain things
so for example if we have this 2d array here we have two axes axis zero which goes down along the rows
and then we have axis 1 which goes left and right along the columns here
so we can do an example here where we're going to be combining values along different axes
so let's define the exact same array that we have in this diagram over here
and first we'll start by doing np.sum
so by defualt if you use any of these operations like np.sum it's going to basically combine all the elements of your array into a single number
maybe you only want to add all the numbers along a certain direction
특정 방향을 따라 숫자가
so let's say I want to add these three things together to get 14
these three to get 15 and so on and these two together get nine
I can specify that I only want to do the summation along axis zero
so here what that's going to do is it'll only do the summation along each column
but it's going to keep those values and not combine them together
and similarly I can specify axis 1 and that's going to do it along the
하고 함께 결합하지
it's going to add up all the items in each row so this way this way
this pretty much works like any kind of reduction operation you could do in numpy
for example, like max and min you can specify axes
and so if I do the max along x is zero then that's going to give me the largest number along each of these columns
If I do maximum axis one then I'm going to get the largest item along each of these rows
경우 이러한 각 열을 따라 가장 큰 숫자를 제공하면
so it's really useful to kind of understand what exactly these axes are reffering to
because a lot of times
you're going to be working with operations where you don't want to reduce the entire array
but you want to keep maybe one of the dimensions
so more generally once we start talking about things with more than two dimensions in numpy
It's the best to think of an axis as basically the index of one of the values in the arrays dot shape property
so let's look at an example here where we're going to create an array with random numbers between one to ten
1에서 10 사이의 난수로 배열을 생성할 예
and this is going to be the shape it's going to have four different dimensions 3 by 2 by 4 by 5
3 x 2
and if you do some kind of reduction operation and specify a certain axis
what that basically does is combine the values along that axis
or you can think of it as that axis basically disappearing from the erase shape
then
so if I do np.sum along axis 2
this number
the second index of the shape is going to disappear
and the result is going to be 3 by 2 by 5
and similarly you can also specify multiple axes like
모양의 두 번째 인덱스
in this case maybe I want to add everything along x to zero
but also along axis 2 and
it'll do this reduction
across both axes
both are going to disappear and you're going to be left with a 2 by 5 array