hello and welcome to the second lecture
of cs285
today we're going to talk about
supervised learning of behaviors
so let's start with a little bit of
terminology and notation
if we have a regular supervised learning
problem
let's say a computer vision problem an
object recognition problem
we might want to recognize objects in an
image so we might have some input image
that goes through a deep neural network
and the output is a label
so the terminology we're going to use
here
is going to be kind of reinforcement
learning terminology and i'll gradually
work from
using reinforcement terminology from us
for a standard supervised learning
example
to then turn that into a reinforcement
learning problem
so we're going to call the input o for
observation
and we're going to call the output a for
action but for now the input is an image
and the output is a label
the neural network in the middle or in
general whatever kind of model you might
want to have
that maps the observations to actions
we're going to call
policy and we'll denote it with the the
letter pi
where the subscript theta represents the
parameters of that policy so in a neural
net
theta represents the weights of that
neural net so we have an input
o an output a and a mapping between them
pi
subscript theta which gives a
distribution over a
given o
now in reinforcement learning of course
we're concerned with
sequential decision making problems so
all of these inputs and outputs
occur at some point in time so we'll
typically use a subscript
t to denote the time step at which they
happen usually in reinforcement learning
we deal with discrete time problems so
we assume that
time is broken up into little discrete
steps and t is an integer that
represents
at which step do you observe o and at
which step do you
emit a so now pi theta
gives a distribution over a t
conditional ot
and of course unlike regular supervised
learning in reinforcement learning
the output at one time step influences
the input
at the next so a t has an effect on ot
plus one so if you for example
fail to recognize the tiger then at the
next time step
you might see something undesirable like
maybe the tiger will be a lot closer to
you
so you could extend this basic idea
to learn policies
for control so obviously instead of
outputting labels you would probably
output something
that looks a lot more like an action but
it could still be a discrete action it
could still
use a soft max distribution so for
instance you could choose from a
discrete set of options
upon seeing the tiger but you could also
have a continuous action
in which case pi theta outputs the
parameters of some continuous
distribution
such as the mean and variance of a
multivariate normal or gaussian
distribution
so to summarize the terminology ot
represents the observation
a t represents the action and then
pi subscript theta a t given ot
is the policy
now another term that we'll see a lot in
reinforcement learning
is the state which we'll denote as st
and sometimes we'll see the policy
written as a t
given st the difference between
st and ot is that the state is typically
assumed to be a markovian state which
i'll explain shortly
whereas ot is an observation that
results from that state
so most generally we would write a
policy as being conditional and
observation
but sometimes we'll write it as being
conditional and state and that is
a more restrictive special case so let
me explain the distinction
between states and observations
let's say that you observe this scene
there is a cheetah
chasing a gazelle now this observation
consists of an image and the image is
made of pixels
those pixels might be sufficient to
figure out where the cheetah and the
gazelle
are or they might not be but
the image is produced by some underlying
physics
of some system and that system has a
state it has a kind of a minimal
representation
so the image is the observation ot the
state
is the representation of the current
configuration of the system
which in this case might be for instance
the position of the cheetah and the
position of the gazelle
and maybe their velocities
now the observation might be altered in
some way
so the full state cannot be inferred
exactly for instance if a car
drives in front of the cheetah and you
can't see it
the observation might be insufficient to
deduce the state
but the state hasn't actually changed
the cheat is still where it was before
is just that now the image pixels and
the observation are not enough
to figure out where it is and that
really
gets at the difference between states
and observations states
are the true configuration of the system
an observation
is something that results from that
state which may or may not be enough
to deduce the state more formally
we can explain the distinction between
states and observations
by using the terminology of graphical
models
so we can draw a graphical model that
represents the relationship
between states and actions and
observations as i mentioned observations
result from states
so there's an arrow from s to o at every
time step
your policy uses the observations to
choose the action so that's the arrow
from o to a
and the state in action at the current
time step determines the state of the
next time step so s1 and a1
go to s2
now from inspecting this graphical model
we might conclude that there are certain
independencies
that are present in the system so
this is the policy pi this is the
transition probabilities p of s d plus
one given s t
a t and something we might note here
is that
p of s t plus 1 given s t 18
is independent of s t minus 1. so for a
state
if you know the current state then you
can figure out the distribution over the
next state
without any regard for the previous
state
that is to say the future is
conditionally independent of the past
given the present this is a very
important independence property
because it says that if you want to make
a decision
that will impact future states
you do not have to consider how you
reach the state you're currently in it's
enough to just consider your current
state and you can forget about previous
states
that led you to it this is called the
markov property and the markov property
is a very very important property in
reinforcement learning and sequential
decision making
because without the markov property we
would not be able to formulate
optimal policies without considering
entire histories
however if our policy is conditioned on
observations rather than states
as it is in this picture we could ask
well
are the observations also conditionally
independent in this way
is the current observation entirely
sufficient
to figure out how to act so as to reach
some state in the future
take a moment to think about this
question and consider writing your
answer in the comments
the trouble is that the observation is
in general not
going to satisfy the markov property
meaning that the current observation
might not be enough to fully determine
the future without also observing the
past
and this is perhaps most obvious from
the example with the cheetah
when the car is in front of the cheetah
and you cannot see where it is in the
image
you might not be able to figure out
where it's going to go in the future
because you can't see it right now
but if in the previous point in time you
could see if maybe the car was somewhere
else before
you could memorize where the cheetah was
so that even when it's occluded by the
car you still remember its state
so in general if you're using
observations past observations can
actually give you additional information
beyond what you would get from the
current observation
that would be useful for decision making
whereas if you directly observe states
then the current state is always going
to give you everything you need
because it satisfies the markov property
now many reinforcement learning
algorithms that we'll discuss in this
course
will actually require markovian
states in which case i will write pi of
a given s
but in some cases i will also mention
that a particular algorithm
could be modified in some way to handle
non-markovian observations
and then i'll describe how that can be
done
now a little aside on notation in
reinforcement learning we typically use
s to denote state and a to denote action
that's very reasonable because those are
the first letters of those words in
english
this kind of terminology was
widely popularized by the study of
dynamic programming which in many ways
was
kind of pioneered by richard bellman in
the 1950s
if you have a background in robotics and
optimal control and linear systems
then you might be more familiar with a
different notation where
x is used to denote state and u is used
to denote action
this is exactly equivalent terminology x
makes sense for state because
that's usually the variable used for an
unknown quantity in algebra
and u is the first word for action in
russian which is
and uh this makes sense because this
kind of terminology
was actually popularized by folks like
left panteragan
who studied optimal control in the
soviet union
all right so that's a little bit of
terminology
but let's talk now about how we can
actually learn
policies and in today's lecture we'll
actually start with a very simple way of
learning policies
that doesn't even require using very
sophisticated reinforcement learning
algorithms
but instead learns policies in much the
same way that we learn
image classifiers and other kinds of
models in supervised learning
by utilizing data
so let's go to a more realistic example
running away from tigers is maybe
not so important in our daily lives but
how about another task the task of
driving
in driving your observations might
consist of
images from the cars camera and your
action might consist of how you turn the
steering wheel in order to keep the car
on the road
so let's uh kind of take an approach to
driving similar to what we might do
in uh you know for things like image
classification computer vision
and so on let's just take some label
data and use that label data
to learn a driving policy with
supervised learning so we'll get an
image from a person and their
corresponding motor commands so this
human driver will have
turned the steering wheel in some way
and will record what they saw from a
camera
and will record the steering command and
we'll collect a large data set
consisting of image and action tuples
and then we'll simply use supervised
learning
to learn to map from observations to
actions
this is called imitation learning and
this is a particular instance of
invitational learning that is sometimes
referred to
as behavioral cloning it's called
behavioral cloning because in a sense we
are cloning
the behavior of this human demonstrator
the demonstrators also sometimes refer
to as an expert because we assume that
they are better at this task
than the computer is all right
so this is a very simple approach and we
could ask the question well
does it actually work
um so this question has uh
has been studied for a very long time in
fact the original
deep imitation imitation learning system
or neural limitation learning system
something that would be familiar to us
today
was proposed all the way back in 1989
it was called alvin the autonomous land
vehicle and neural network
and alvin did some pretty interesting
things the network by current standards
was tiny had five hidden units
but it could do you know interesting
behaviors like staying on a road
and there were some attempts to even try
to drive it across america
so we could ask does this uh basic
principle work does this behavior
cloning principle work
in general the answer is no and to give
you a little bit of intuition
for why behavioral cloning might go
wrong even while regular supervised
learning would work