in the next part of today's lecture
we're going to cover a little bit of imitation learning theory
building off of this notion of cost functions and reward functions
so we'll ask this question what is a good cost function
or reward function for imitation learning
so this is the sketch limitation learning from before
we're going to be mapping observations to actions
and we could hypothesize that maybe a reasonable reward function
might be the log probability that we assign to the experts action
so the log probability of the action that we take is equal to *pi of s
where *pi is the unknown policy of the expert
we could also use something called the 0 1 loss so we might say
we get a loss of zero if we perfectly
match the expert
and a one if we didn't the zero one loss
is a bit more
uh convenient for theoretical analysis
and it directly counts the number of
mistakes that you make
whereas the log likelihood is a bit more
of a practical choice
but remember that in reinforcement
learning
the reward or loss must be evaluated in
expectation
under the learned policy not under the
policy of the expert
so we want to match the experts actions
in the states that we actually visit not necessarily just in the states that the expert visited
and this is why behavior cloning is not
actually optimizing quite the right
objective behavior cloning would typically
maximize the log likelihood in expectation
under the state or observation
distribution of the expert
whereas we want to maximize it in expectation
under the state or observation distribution
of our policy this is another way of saying
that we have a distributional mismatch problem
and this is exactly the problem that
dagger tries to correct
so what i'm going to do next is i'm
going to theoretically analyze
some bounds on the expected cost
for naive behavior cloning
and discuss how we can formalize
this distributional shift problem
so in this analysis i'm going to use T
to denote the length of the trajectory
so if we see me use T
that just means there are T
steps in our trajectory
and we're going to be concerned with
this zero one loss
and the quantity that we want to analyze is
the expected total value of the zero one loss
which is also the expected number of
mistakes we would make along one trajectory
so in order to do any kind of analysis like
this we have to first make some assumptions
and the assumption that i'm going to
make is that
supervised learning works what that means is initially
i'll make a fairly naive assumption which is
that for all of the states
in the training set the probability of
making a mistake at those states
is less than or equal to epsilon
this is a reasonable assumption because
it says for the state and action tuples
that you saw you learned them effectively meaning
that if someone told you in state s
take action a you're going to assign a
probability less than or equal to epsilon to every
other action where epsilon is some small number
and now in order to think about bounding
the total number of mistakes
we're going to consider the most
pessimistic scenario possible
when we construct theoretical bounds we
want to be pessimistic we want to
write down some inequality that holds in
the worst possible case
and the most pessimistic scenario for
these zero one losses is
what i'm going to call a tightrope
walker scenario
so for a tank rope walker the tightrope
walker needs to take exactly the right action
at every single point in time
and if they make even a single mistake
they fall off the tightrope
and then they don't know what to do
so we can illustrate the type of walker
schematically as this grid world
where they have to stay on the gray
squares and keep going to the right
and if they deviate even once they fall
off they go into the red region
where there is no demonstration data
because the expert never fell off
and therefore they have no way of
knowing what to do
now this type of walker just to be clear
is not concerned with falling off
because they'll get hurt they're
concerned about falling off
because they will incur zero one loss
when they fall off
they'll be in a state where they have no data
which means that they have no way
of knowing what to do in that state
so it's a kind of a funny type of walker
their concern is not about hurting
themselves
their concern is about not knowing what
to do
okay so let's analyze this type of
walker
so the quantity that we want to bound
is the sum over time of the zero one loss
which is the expected number of mistakes
let's think about the first time step at
the very first time step
the title walker starts in a state that
was in the training set
which means that with probability uh
greater than epsilon
they will take the correct action with
probability
less than or equal to epsilon they'll
take the wrong action
if they take the wrong action they will fall off
but they still have T
time steps left and once they fall off
they have no way of knowing what to do
so if they fall off
they will make an additional T
mistakes
so we can say that for that first time step
there's an epsilon term which
represents the probability of falling off
and if they fall off they will get
capital t additional mistakes
so there's an epsilon times capital t term
and then there's a one minus epsilon times
everything else so epsilon times T
plus one minus epsilon times the number of mistakes
that they will make at the next time step until the end
and what happens at the next time step well
the same exact thing at the next time step
if they did the right thing on the first time step
they again have an epsilon probability of falling off
now there's only t minus one steps left
so they fall off on the second step
they will get epsilon times t minus 1 plus 1
minus epsilon times whatever is left over so
you get this series of terms epsilon t + 1 - epsilon x epsilon t -
1 + 1 - epsilon x 1 - epsilon times epsilon t - 2 etc etc etc
so you basically get T terms
and each one of them is on the order of
epsilon t
right when we're concerned with big o
we can get rid of uh constants in front
and since 1 - epsilon is usually a
pretty large number
all we're really getting is a bunch of
these epsilon t terms
so that means that the total bound is
T times epsilon t
so the error is on the order of
epsilon t^2 right technically it's
going to be like
epsilon times t t squared over two
or something like that
but if we're just concerned with big o uh
then we don't care about those constants
and we got epsilon t squared now this is
a pretty bad bound
because it means that the as our
the length of our trajectory increases
our error increases quadratically
and that's why naive behavioral
cloning can be a bad idea theoretically
now that analysis was a little bit naive
because we didn't assume anything about
generalization we just said that
for all states in the training set our
errors bounded by epsilon
a more general analysis would account for
generalization would account for the fact
that your policy does well not just on
the training points
but on other points from the same
distribution
so one way that we could say this is
we could say our error is bounded by
epsilon
for any state sampled from p train
in fact it's actually enough just to say that our error
is bounded for by epsilon in expectation or p train
and that's much more realistic because
that's our actual training objective
for the analysis i'm going to present
i'll go with the the
uh the s sample from p train definition
but this is actually fairly easy to extend
uh to the setting where your expected error is
bounded by epsilon and that's what's actually done
uh in the stephon ross dagger paper
so here's how we can go about this more
sophisticated analysis so first
uh with that just to get this out of the
way with dagger
p train approaches p theta right that's
the whole point of dagger
so if p train approaches p theta then
all points will be in distribution
which means that s is always sampled
from p train
which means that error is always bounded
by epsilon
which means that no matter what you do
the bound on the expected cost will be
epsilon times t it'll be linear in t
that's in some ways not actually all
that interesting of a result
because we're removing all distributional shift
what's more interesting is how we
can show that the bound is still quadratic
if we don't do dagger if we if we don't
have p train going to be theta
and that's what we're going to do next on
this side so if p train is not equal to p theta
then what we can do and then this
analysis is basically
directly based on stefan ross's paper a reduction
of imitation learning and structural prediction
to no regret online learning which is
the docker paper
what we can do is we can write the distribution over
states at some time step t as the sum of two terms
and these two terms are kind of
analogous to the type of walker scenario
the first term represents what happened
if we haven't made a mistake
at any previous time step and the second term represents
what happens if we did
so for the first term what's the probability
that we haven't made a mistake so far
well our probability of doing the right thing
if we're in distribution is one
minus epsilon
and if we do the right thing then we
remain in distribution
which means that by time step little t
we have a probability of one minus
epsilon to the power t
then we've done the right stuff up
until now and we've done the right stuff
up until now then our state distribution
is simply p train
because we've matched the expert every single step up until
now so the first term is 1 minus epsilon to the power
of t times p train the second term is everything else
1 minus 1 minus epsilon to the t so this
basically accounts
for all the other probability mass and
if we have made a mistake in the past
in general we can't really say anything
about where we're at
so we might have fallen off the
tightrope we might be in some crazy place
so we're going to call that p mistake
so what this is saying is that for at
any time step we can write the
distribution over states
as the sum of two terms the first one
for not having made any mistakes
and the second one for having made at
least one mistake
now in general we can't say anything
about p mistake
so for p mistake we might have arbitrarily
large probability of additional error
so what we can do is we can bound the total variation divergence
between p theta s t and p train st
total variation divergence is just the sum of the
absolute values of the differences
between the probabilities over all the states
so if we take the left-hand side of this
equation
and substitute in the above equation for
p theta
basically substitute in 1 minus epsilon to the t times b
train plus 1 minus 1 minus epsilon to the t times p mistake
the first p train term cancels with the minus sign and we just end up with 1
minus 1 minus epsilon to the t of the absolute value of p mistake minus p train
now remember that we can't say anything
about p mistake
so the only bound that we can put on the
total variation divergence
between p mistake and p train is the maximum
error between two distributions which is two right
because the distribution sum to one
in the worst case one of them will be
one in one place and the other will be
zero
the other only one in another place
where the other one is zero
so the only bound that we can put on
this if we don't know anything about p mistake
is 2 times 1 minus 1 minus epsilon of t
a useful identity that we can use to
simplify this is that 1 minus epsilon to
the t
is greater than or equal to 1 minus
epsilon times t
if epsilon is between zero and one and
we know that epsilon is between zero and
one because epsilon is a bound on a
probability
and probabilities are always less than
one and always positive
so we can write a simpler bound for this
by turning this into two times epsilon t
we don't have to do this this is a
looser bound but it's just convenient
to remove the exponential and to give us kind of an
understanding of the big o magnitude of this okay
so now let's go to the quantity that we really want what we
care about is the expected value of the cost overall time
so we can write the expected value of
the cost uh as a sum over time
of a sum over states of the probability of that state times
the cost that's just from the definition of expected value
and we can express this uh we can express a bound on
this cost in terms of two terms p train times the cost
plus the difference between p theta and
p train
the way that you get this inequality is
just by writing
p theta is equal to p theta plus p train
minus p
train right if you add and subtract
something that's all good
then we group the terms and we put absolute value
around p theta minus p train
because the absolute value of a number
is always greater than or equal to
that number itself so that's how we can get
this bound
now the first part p
train times c we know what that is
because the expected value under p train
of the cost
is bounded by epsilon that's our
assumption
the second term well the
bound that we have above on the absolute value of p theta minus p train
is two times epsilon t and c max the worst case cost is one
so then the bound that we can write out for this is epsilon that comes from the
expected value of the constant or p train plus two times epsilon t
which comes from the total variation divergence
or absolute value between p theta and p train
so we have one term that's linear in
T and one term that's quadratic
because the sum over t of two epsilon t
is on the order of capital t squared
so we've derived an o of epsilon t squared
bound with this kind of more general assumption
and notice here that uh the only
assumption on the policy
that we needed is that the expected value of the cost
under p train is epsilon so this is kind of the
more general assumption that i stated before
all right so this derivation maybe went
by a little fast
so if you have any questions about this
do feel free to ask a comment on youtube
we can discuss this in class
and also consider checking out the paper
cited below by stefan ross that
describes the full proof in detail