hello and welcome to the second lecture
of cs285
today we're going to talk about
supervised learning of behaviors
so let's start with a little bit of
terminology and notation
if we have a regular supervised learning
problem
let's say a computer vision problem an
object recognition problem
we might want to recognize objects in an image
so we might have some input image
that goes through a deep neural network
and the output is a label
so the terminology we're going to use
here is going to be kind of reinforcement learning terminology
and i'll gradually
work from
using reinforcement terminology from us
for a standard supervised learning example
to then turn that into a reinforcement
learning problem
so we're going to call the input o for
observation
and we're going to call the output a for action
but for now the input is an image
and the output is a label
the neural network in the middle or in general
whatever kind of model you might want to have
that maps the observations to actions
we're going to call policy
and we'll denote it with the the
letter pi
where the subscript theta represents the
parameters of that policy
so in a neural net
theta represents the weights of that neural net
so we have an input o an output a and a mapping between them
pi subscript theta which gives a distribution over a given o
now in reinforcement learning of course
we're concerned with
sequential decision making problems
so all of these inputs and outputs
occur at some point in time
so we'll typically use a subscript
t to denote the time step at which they happen
usually in reinforcement learning
we deal with discrete time problems
so we assume that
time is broken up into little discrete steps
and t is an integer that
represents at which step do you observe o
and at which step do you emit a
so now pi theta gives a
distribution over a t conditional ot
and of course unlike regular supervised learning
in reinforcement learning the output
at one time step influences the input at the next
so a t has an effect on ot plus one
so if you for example fail to recognize
the tiger then at the next time step
you might see something undesirable like
maybe the tiger will be a lot closer to you
so you could extend this basic idea
to learn policies
for control so obviously instead of outputting
labels you would probably output something
that looks a lot more like an action but it
could still be a discrete action it could still use a soft max distribution
so for instance
you could choose from a discrete set of options upon seeing the tiger
but you could also
have a continuous action
in which case pi theta outputs the
parameters of some continuous distribution
such as the mean and variance of a
multivariate normal or gaussian distribution
so to summarize the terminology ot
represents the observation
a t represents the action
and then pi subscript theta a t given ot
is the policy
now another term that we'll see a lot in
reinforcement learning
is the state which we'll denote as st
and sometimes we'll see the policy
written as a t given st
the difference between st and ot
is that the state is typically assumed to be
a markovian state which i'll explain shortly
whereas ot is an observation that
results from that state
so most generally we would write a
policy as being conditional and observation
but sometimes we'll write it as being conditional and
state and that is a more restrictive special case
so let me explain the distinction
between states and observations
let's say that you observe this scene
there is a cheetah chasing a gazelle
now this observation consists of an
image and the image is made of pixels
those pixels might be sufficient to figure
out where the cheetah and the gazelle are
or they might not be
but the image is produced
by some underlying physics of some system
and that system has a state it has
a kind of a minimal representation
so the image is the observation ot
the state is the representation of
the current configuration of the system
which in this case might be for instance the position
of the cheetah and the position of the gazelle
and maybe their velocities
now the observation might be altered in
some way
so the full state cannot be inferred
exactly for instance if a car
drives in front of the cheetah and you
can't see it
the observation might be insufficient to
deduce the state
but the state hasn't actually changed
the cheat is still where it was before
is just that now the image pixels and
the observation are not enough
to figure out where it is and that
really
gets at the difference between states
and observations states
are the true configuration of the system
an observation
is something that results from that
state which may or may not be enough
to deduce the state more formally
we can explain the distinction between
states and observations
by using the terminology of graphical
models
so we can draw a graphical model that
represents the relationship
between states and actions and
observations as i mentioned observations
result from states
so there's an arrow from s to o at every
time step
your policy uses the observations to
choose the action so that's the arrow
from o to a
and the state in action at the current
time step determines the state of the
next time step so s1 and a1
go to s2
now from inspecting this graphical model
we might conclude that there are certain
independencies
that are present in the system so
this is the policy pi this is the
transition probabilities p of s d plus
one given s t
a t and something we might note here
is that
p of s t plus 1 given s t 18
is independent of s t minus 1. so for a
state
if you know the current state then you
can figure out the distribution over the
next state
without any regard for the previous
state
that is to say the future is
conditionally independent of the past
given the present this is a very
important independence property
because it says that if you want to make
a decision
that will impact future states
you do not have to consider how you
reach the state you're currently in it's
enough to just consider your current
state and you can forget about previous
states
that led you to it this is called the
markov property and the markov property
is a very very important property in
reinforcement learning and sequential
decision making
because without the markov property we
would not be able to formulate
optimal policies without considering
entire histories
however if our policy is conditioned on
observations rather than states
as it is in this picture we could ask
well
are the observations also conditionally
independent in this way
is the current observation entirely
sufficient
to figure out how to act so as to reach
some state in the future
take a moment to think about this
question and consider writing your
answer in the comments
the trouble is that the observation is
in general not
going to satisfy the markov property
meaning that the current observation
might not be enough to fully determine
the future without also observing the
past
and this is perhaps most obvious from
the example with the cheetah
when the car is in front of the cheetah
and you cannot see where it is in the
image
you might not be able to figure out
where it's going to go in the future
because you can't see it right now
but if in the previous point in time you
could see if maybe the car was somewhere
else before
you could memorize where the cheetah was
so that even when it's occluded by the
car you still remember its state
so in general if you're using
observations past observations can
actually give you additional information
beyond what you would get from the
current observation
that would be useful for decision making
whereas if you directly observe states
then the current state is always going
to give you everything you need
because it satisfies the markov property
now many reinforcement learning
algorithms that we'll discuss in this
course
will actually require markovian
states in which case i will write pi of
a given s
but in some cases i will also mention
that a particular algorithm
could be modified in some way to handle
non-markovian observations
and then i'll describe how that can be
done
now a little aside on notation in
reinforcement learning we typically use
s to denote state and a to denote action
that's very reasonable because those are
the first letters of those words in
english
this kind of terminology was
widely popularized by the study of
dynamic programming which in many ways
was
kind of pioneered by richard bellman in
the 1950s
if you have a background in robotics and
optimal control and linear systems
then you might be more familiar with a
different notation where
x is used to denote state and u is used
to denote action
this is exactly equivalent terminology x
makes sense for state because
that's usually the variable used for an
unknown quantity in algebra
and u is the first word for action in
russian which is
and uh this makes sense because this
kind of terminology
was actually popularized by folks like
left panteragan
who studied optimal control in the
soviet union
all right so that's a little bit of
terminology
but let's talk now about how we can
actually learn
policies and in today's lecture we'll
actually start with a very simple way of
learning policies
that doesn't even require using very
sophisticated reinforcement learning
algorithms
but instead learns policies in much the
same way that we learn
image classifiers and other kinds of
models in supervised learning
by utilizing data
so let's go to a more realistic example
running away from tigers is maybe
not so important in our daily lives but
how about another task the task of
driving
in driving your observations might
consist of
images from the cars camera and your
action might consist of how you turn the
steering wheel in order to keep the car
on the road
so let's uh kind of take an approach to
driving similar to what we might do
in uh you know for things like image
classification computer vision
and so on let's just take some label
data and use that label data
to learn a driving policy with
supervised learning so we'll get an
image from a person and their
corresponding motor commands so this
human driver will have
turned the steering wheel in some way
and will record what they saw from a
camera
and will record the steering command and
we'll collect a large data set
consisting of image and action tuples
and then we'll simply use supervised
learning
to learn to map from observations to
actions
this is called imitation learning and
this is a particular instance of
invitational learning that is sometimes
referred to
as behavioral cloning it's called
behavioral cloning because in a sense we
are cloning
the behavior of this human demonstrator
the demonstrators also sometimes refer
to as an expert because we assume that
they are better at this task
than the computer is all right
so this is a very simple approach and we
could ask the question well
does it actually work
um so this question has uh
has been studied for a very long time in
fact the original
deep imitation imitation learning system
or neural limitation learning system
something that would be familiar to us
today
was proposed all the way back in 1989
it was called alvin the autonomous land
vehicle and neural network
and alvin did some pretty interesting
things the network by current standards
was tiny had five hidden units
but it could do you know interesting
behaviors like staying on a road
and there were some attempts to even try
to drive it across america
so we could ask does this uh basic
principle work does this behavior
in general the answer is no and to give you a little bit of intuition
for why behavioral cloning might go wrong even while regular supervised learning would work
uh let's uh start with a very kind of abstract picture of a control problem
so i'll draw a lot of pictures like this in today's lecture
when i draw a picture like this  the axis on the left represents the state
now of course in general the state is not one-dimensional
but i'll have this axis be one-dimensional so that it's easier to visualize
and then the other axis represents time
so this black curve represents the trajectory through time at every point in time
there's a different value of the state
and let's say that this black trajectory represents our training data
so we're going to take this as our training data use it to train a policy
that goes from s to a and then we'll run that policy
so now in red i'm going to draw what this policy will do when we run it
initially the policy stays pretty close to the training data
because we're going to use a large neural network and will train it very well
but it does make some small mistakes
every learned model will make at least some small mistakes this is basically inevitable
the trouble is that when this model makes some small mistake
it will find itself in a state that's just a little bit different
than the states that it was trained on
and when it finds itself in a state that is unusual that is different from the training states
it'll make a bigger mistake because it doesn't quite know what to do there
and as these mistakes compound the state becomes more and more different
and the mistakes get bigger and bigger
until after a while the learned policy might end up doing something very different
from the demonstrated behavior
so you could imagine the car scenario
the car will veer a little to the left just a tiny bit
then see something unfamiliar and here
to the left a little more until eventually goes off the road
and we'll see we'll discard describe this phenomenon much more formally later on in in the lecture
but does this work in practice well
in practice actually sometimes it's pretty effective
so these videos are collected from a paper uh released by nvidia in 2016
and you can see that initially they had a lot of trouble with the system
it would kind of go off the road do some messy things run into cones
but after collecting a lot of data and using a few little tricks
they actually ended up with a system
that did something fairly sensible
that could autonomously drive between the cones
stay on the road and exhibit some you know fairly reasonable behavior
so why is that why is it that we can use behavioral cloning methods in practice
to train policies that actually do something fairly decent well
we'll discuss this in more detail in part two
but one of the things that i want to mention briefly now is
the particular technique that was used to address this issue in this paper by nvidia
so if we look at the paper and we look at the their description of their system
it mostly looks very much like what we expect so the there is a conv-net
the conv-net produces a steering angle
the you know the the car tracks that steering angle the conv-net takes this input
camera inputs but something that you might notice here is that
there's a center camera left camera and right camera
well it turns out that one of the tricks
that was used in this paper which turns out to be kind of important
is that you record three different camera images at the same time
one pointing forward one left and one right
the forward image is supervised with whatever steering angle the person had
the image looking to the left is supervised of the steering angle
that is a little bit to the right of what the person did
so that means that if the car saw an image that was going left off the road
it should steer to the right
and correspondingly the image pointed to
the right is supervised with a term to the left
now you can imagine how this particular trick in the special case of driving a car
would actually mitigate this drifting problem
because now these left and right images
are essentially teaching the policy how to correct little mistakes
and if i can correct those mistakes
then maybe they won't accumulate as much
now this is a special case of a more general principle
the more general principle is that while errors in the trajectory will compound
if you can somehow modify your training data
so that your training data illustrates little mistakes and
feedbacks to correct those mistakes
then perhaps the policy can learn those feedbacks and stabilize
and there are a number of different ways to do this some of them will discuss later on in the course
for example if you train a stable optimal feedback controller around the demonstration
and use that feedback controller as supervision you can actually get stable policies
that inherit that stability
or you can simply ask a person to potentially make mistakes and correct those mistakes
so there are little tricks like this
that we can use to try to patch the issue
but something that we could ask
also to derive a more general solution
is what's the kind of the underlying mathematical principle behind this drift
what's really going on here
well when we run the policy
we're sampling from pi theta a t given ot
and this distribution pi theta a t given ot
it was trained on some data distribution
and that data distribution we'll call it p data ot
this is basically the distribution of observations
seen in our training data
now we know from supervised learning theory that
when you train a particular model on a particular training distribution
and you get good training error and you don't over fit
fthen you would expect to also get good test error
if test points are drawn from the same distribution
so if we see new observations
that come from the same distribution as our training data
even if the observations themselves are not the same
we would expect our learned policy to produce the right action on those observations
however when we run our policy
the distribution over observations that we actually see is different
the observation over the the distribution of observations is different
because the policy takes different actions
which result in different observations
so after a while p pi theta o t
becomes very different from p data ot
and this is the reason for this compounding error problem
so can we somehow fix this can we make p data ot
equal to p pi theta ot if we could do this
then we know that our policy would produce good actions
simply from standard results in supervised learning theory
now one way to make p data ot equal to p pi theta ot
is to simply make the policy perfect
if the policy is perfect and it never makes mistakes
then these distributions will match
but that's of course very very hard
so what if instead of being clever about our policy
we're actually we can try to actually be clever about our data distribution
so let's maybe not change the policy in some clever way
but let's actually change our data to avoid this distributional shift problem
that's the basic idea behind a method called dagger
dagger stands for "Dataset Aggregation"
so in dagger, our goal is to collect training data
that comes from p pi theta ot instead of p data ot
because if we have observation action tuples
from p pi theta o t and we train on those observation action tuples
then the distributional shift problem will be gone
so here's how dagger accomplishes this
we're going to actually run
pi theta a t given ot
which will produce samples from p by theta ot
and then we'll request additional labels at those observations
so step one is to initialize our policy
by training on the human dataset
then we're going to run our policy to
collect an additional data set of observations
that i'm denoting here as d pi and
these observations now come from p by theta o t
then we'll ask a human to label all of these observations with optimal actions
so someone will literally watch the observations that the machine produced
and tell the machine what the optimal action
that they would have taken for those observations actually is
and then we will aggregate
we will actually merge these data sets
and then train the policy on it again
now when we train the policy again on this merged data set
the policy will change
which means that even though our observations in d pi came from p pi theta
now theta is different and p by theta is also different
so we have to repeat this process
but we can actually show and this is shown in the paper by ross at all
that introduced this algorithm that repeating this process enough times
eventually does extra converge
resulting in a final data set that does come from the same distribution as the policy asymptotically
so here's an example of a policy trained with dagger
flying a drone through a forest
this policy doesn't actually use a deep neural network
it actually uses some linear image features
but subsequent work has done this with deep neural networks as well
so this drone initially was not able to deflect far forest very well
but after a few iterations of soliciting additional labels from the human
it was able to navigate the forest quite proficiently
so what is the issue with dagger
why don't we always use this algorithm in invitation learning (imitaition?)
well a lot of the issues with dagger really come from step three
it's a little bit problem dependent
but in many cases asking a human to manually label dpi with optimal actions
can actually be quite onerous
imagine doing this yourself
imagine that you're watching a video of a drone flying through a forest
and you have to steer that drone provide optimal actions
without your actions actually affecting the drone in real time
that's very unnatural to humans because
humans don't just map observations to actions in open loop
we actually do feedback control
we watch the effect of our actions and compensate accordingly
when you can't see the effect of your actions
it can be a little hard to do this
so this is of course situational
in some domains providing optimal
actions for arbitrary observations
can be reasonably straightforward such
as an abstract decision making problems
like for example if you're doing
operations research inventory management
et cetera
it's easy to ask an expert you know if
your warehouse is in this state and your
prices are this
how should you change the prices but
it's comparatively much hard ask a human
if you see this image how should you
turn the steering wheel
all right