all right now let's go over a full
example to see the whole process of
defining a neural network training it
and then using it to make predictions
so the task we'll have is to use a
neural network to model a sine wave
so this is our target
this is the function we're trying to learn and
we'll start by defining the architecture
of our neural network the way we'll do
that is using something called modules
so the base class
for pretty much all the layers of neural
networks in PyTorch is something called
an nn.Module and this module basically
represents the building block of the
full computation graph
so typically
your neural network might have things
like convolution layers fully connected layers
pooling things like that and each of those
is a subclass of nn.Module and those
three actually have already been defined for you in PyTorch
so when you want to define your neural
network you would just piece together a
bunch of these modules into your own module
for the overall network
so as an example let's take this model
which we
sort of saw in the first video
so we have three operations the first
two are linear followed by non-linearity
and the last one is just going to be a
linear transformation to get a scalar
output value
so this is the architecture we're going to use
for this problem
so in order to define this architecture
we're going to define a class in python
you can call whatever you want we'll
call it that in this case but the
important thing is that we want it to be
a subclass of an end module
so what you're going to do is you
typically need two things within your class
in the constructor you're going to define
all the layers of your model and in this
forward function you're going to define
what it does on an input
and return some output as the prediction
so in our constructor
we have a three layers we need to define
uh one two and three over here so we're
gonna define those as fc1 through fc3
and each of those is going to be using a
built-in nn.linear class which is a
subclass of nn.Module and we can
specify what we want the inputs and
outputs to look like
then for the forward pass we're going to define
what PyTorch what this model actually
does to make a prediction so here we're
going to send it through a linear layer
then a related non-linearity
do that again a second time for the
second hidden layer and then for the
last layer we're just going to do
a linear transformation and then return the output
so once this has been defined you can
initialize instances of your network
just like you would with any python class
and when you print it out
you can see this nice representation of
what your neural network looks like and
you can see all the layers you can see
their names and you can see
what their
what their input and output shapes are
so when you want to actually evaluate
this neural net on some input
the way you should do it is by
calling it directly and passing the
input so we initialized a variable net
we're going to call it directly and pass an x
you want to be really careful not to
call net dot forward x
like we're not just going to be calling
the forward pass of uh this class that
we did earlier
and the reason is because what calling
net directly does is uh there's some
like initial setup code that's taken
care of for you and then after that it
it like actually calls net.forward
so you don't want to ever call forward directly
you want to call the module and pass into input
and so once we do this we can see that the
output is just a tensor that has
for the first dimension the same the
same length because this is the batch
dimension we passed in 100
inputs and we get 100 outputs
and the second is just the output size
that we defined earlier in our neural network
so now we can visualize what this
network looks like before training we
have our inputs we have our outputs
and so this is like what our randomly
initialized model is predicting for these values
so if we dive a bit deeper into like what's happening
within this nn.Module
each time you define an instance
variable that's some kind of module
and when this is done within the nn.Module class
what it does is it
it considers it a parameter of your module
and the reason that's significant is
because these parameters will
automatically have their gradients
tracked so requires grad equals true
so if you print these out
you can use
this function called named parameters or
parameters if you just care about the
values and not names and you can see
what layers or what what tensors make up
this model so we had three fully
connected layers each of those fully
connected layers has two temperatures to
represent the operation one for the
weight and one for the bias
and each of these parameters both the
weights and the biases will
automatically have their gradients stored
like we said earlier because they were
defined inside of the nn.Module subclass
so if you print something like this out
you'll see that it has a grad but in
this case it's still none because we
haven't done backprop yet
one common mistake is if you're ever
trying to define a list of modules for
example if you want um to define a
neural network with an arbitrary number
of layers and you maybe use a for loop
to define your individual layers
you don't ever want to just like add
them to a regular python list like this
because if you do that PyTorch won't
recognize that these are actually sub modules
and they won't be considered um actual
parameter module and their gradients
won't be tracked
um so instead the way to do that is by
using this class called nn.ModuleList
and passing in the list of
layers that you actually want to use and
if you do it this way then network one
and network two will both have the gradients tracked properly
so when you make that prediction so earlier
we did
y = net(x) to make a prediction so
when you do that the output is just a tensor
and you can perform operation on the
tensor just like we did before
in all the all the previous videos
and it'll automatically
track the computations and let you
compute derivatives
so here um
for example we're using let's use a
squared loss on our predictions and the target
um and when we call lost.backward()
that's going to automatically run back
prop for us and populate the gradients of
each of the weights of our model
so we can now go into the p.grad
property for each of the parameters of
our model and we can
manually implement gradient descent by
basically like taking a step in the
opposite direction of the gradient
and remember we talked about this before
if you call backward multiple times it's
actually going to keep accumulating the
gradient so if you're going to do
gradient descent
after you do this step you have to
always make sure to zero the gradients
so that next time you start with a fresh copy
and so at this point we pretty much have
all the pieces we need to train our
network we can just use a for loop and
do this repeatedly we compute the loss
call backward to do a backprop and
populate the gradients and then
adjust each of the parameters using the
gradients that were filled in
and then we zero the gradients and start over again
so with that we can get a network that
models something pretty close to our
sine wave so it definitely is learning
but this implementation is kind of
annoying to have to write out every single time
so PyTorch has some
helper functions basically that take
care of certain things for you and so
we'll slowly add those things in and see
how that simplifies our training process
the first thing is loss functions so
PyTorch has a bunch of built-in loss
functions and again these loss functions
are modules just like any other layer
that you had in your model
and you can pass your data through them
so let's say instead of manually
implementing a loss function we
define our loss function to be the mean squared loss
and we can pass in
like the outputs and our targets and we
get some tensor as our output prediction
so now we have the same thing except
we've just replaced
the lost with loss function and you can
see that it will pretty much end up
doing the same thing
so it's not really a big deal here because
our squared loss was pretty easy to
implement but if you ever want to like
experiment with more complicated loss
functions or make it really easy to just
like plug in arbitrary loss functions to
see what works better
this is definitely a good practice to follow
the next thing is optimizers so we'll also use
the optim package within PyTorch
to use some of the built-in optimizers
they have instead of having to manually
implement gradient descent like we did before
so what we'll do is we'll start over
redefine our neural network
and here we have an optimizer and here
you can pretty much use any
optimization function you want you can
use SGD which would most closely match
what we were doing before
you can use RMSprop
or in this case let's just stick with Adam
so it's easy to like plug in different
optimizers you might want and
here uh okay so uh let's make some
predictions and then see what the
network looks like before training again
so again we've reinitialized it so we
should have some random values
and now instead of
manually implementing gradient descent
we'll replace it with the optimizer so
the way that it works is you compute
your loss as usual
but you'll do all optimizations through
the optimizer so first you'll call
optimizer.zero_grad()
which zeroes out all the gradients
then you do lost backward to populate
the gradients of each of your parameters
and then finally you do optimizer.step()
so optimizer.step() is kind of equivalent to
this code that we wrote which basically
updates each of the parameters using a
step of gradient descent
and this optimizer.zero_grad() line is
basically the same thing as
this part of the code where we make sure
to zero the gradients
each time so it doesn't accumulate
so just one thing to be careful of when you
initialize the optimizer you want to
make sure to pass in all the parameters of
whatever neural network or neural
networks you're trying to train
because this is the only way that the
optimizer actually becomes aware of
what it's doing gradient descent on so
when you call like optimizer.zero_grad()
and optimizer.step it'll only actually
update the gradients of the parameters
that you pass in here
um so if you have a single neural
network like we do here it's really easy
you just pass in net.parameters()
but if you ever start working with like
multiple models that are kind of
training simultaneously
you just want to be careful to make sure
that you've actually given the optimizer
all the parameters
okay so now let's run this code
and we can see that it did exactly the
same thing that we had before except now
our code is much more concise
so here's a summary of what we did
feel free to pause the video and
or go back into the colab and just make
sure that you understand
what this whole
training process looks like
next we'll talk about gpu support in PyTorch so most of the time you'll
probably want to do your training on a gpu
because gpus are optimized for matrix
operations and it'll make your training
run much faster
PyTorch makes it pretty easy to move
your tensors between cpu and gpu to
actually do that training process
so we'll see an example of what that
looks like here
first you'll want to check to make sure
you have a gpu available on your current machine
so a lot of you might end up running your
homeworks on colab colab is nice
because it gives you free access to gpus
if you're going to use colab just make
sure that you go into runtime
change runtime type and just make sure
that you have gpu selected otherwise
it's not actually going to be training on gpu
so once that's set
we can print and we can see that
torch.cuda_is_available() is true
and here's an example of
how we can initialize a tensor on gpu
instead of cpu
so by default if you define
some tensor like torch.ones() it's going
to be on cpu but we can specify a device parameter
and tell PyTorch that we actually want
it to be initialized on gpu instead
and you'll notice here it'll specify
devices on something other than cpu
one thing that you really want to be
careful of is you can only do operations
on tensors if they're actually on the same device
so this code will error because we have
x which is on cpu and y which is on gpu
if we try to add them together
we get this error message
so if we wanted to combine them
together we would have to maybe move
x to the gpu and the way we do that if
it was originally initialized on cpu is
using the two function so we just use
x.to() and specify that we want to go to gpu
and this way we can add them together properly
so kind of like you can't convert tensors that have
gradients being tracked into numpy areas
you also can't convert tensors that are
on gpu directly into numpy arrays so if
I do this i'm gonna get an error
so instead if you want to convert to
numpy what you're gonna have to do is
first move it back to cpu and then
convert to numpy
yeah so that kind of adds
uh like another layer of complexity
I could think about when you want to convert tensors to
numpy arrays you have to make sure that
they're detached so they don't have a
gradient you have to transfer them back
to cpu and then you have to convert to
numpy so this can sometimes be kind
of like a headache to track so we have
this nice utility function that will be
available to you on all the homework assignments
it's called ptu.from_numpy() and to_numpy()
and basically what that will do is
from_numpy() will convert a numpy array to
a PyTorch tensor that's on gpu and
to_numpy() will
given a tensor that is on gpu it'll
first move it to cpu and then convert to numpy
so if you use these two functions you
don't really have to think about
whether you're using gpu or not anymore
if it's supported then it's going to do
all of your tensor operations on gpu
okay so now that we've learned a bit about
gpus let's try to incorporate this into
a full training example on that same
sine wave task from before
so this is the full flow of training a model
everything is pretty much the same as before except a few sections are new
after defining the neural network this
is something that you're gonna have to add in if you want gpu support so
basically you define a device usually
it's good practice to define it this way
where we say if it's available then
we'll use gpu if not we use cpu that way
your code is still compatible either way
and then we're going to want to move
both our neural network
and our targets to that new device
usually in practice you're only going to
move the neural network at first you're
not going to move all the targets
because you might be working with like a
huge data set and it's not feasible to
put it all on gpu at once
instead what you do is
work with them in batches just like
when you're doing a
stochastic gradient descent or mini batch gradient descent and
within the for loop for your
gradient descent code you can move each
individual batch to the gpu separately
but here since we have like a pretty
small set of targets we'll just move
them all to the gpu at once
and the other thing we added is here in
the training code um move our input
from cpu to gpu so normally this is
where you would do something like y_target = y.to(device)
oops y_target.to(device)
uh everything else is pretty much the same as before
and we can run this code and you should
notice that it trains a lot faster
the difference will become much more
significant if you start working with
things like images
or higher dimensional data right now
it's kind of a small difference but
you'll definitely want to use it on all
of your homework assignments
so now moving on with our example
we're gonna evaluate the model this is
usually what you would do to
make predictions with a PyTorch model
so notice there are two things we added here
first we want to do net.eval() what that
does is it switches the network to evaluation mode
it doesn't matter for our example but if
your neural network has things like
dropout or batch norm where
it should behave differently during
training and test time you definitely
want to make sure it's in evaluation
mode so that it doesn't
give you inconsistent results
and the next thing is with torch.no_grad()
this is a nice helper function that you should use when you're making
predictions and basically it says that
everything within this block
any tensors that are that are in this
block they're going to have their
requires grad properties set to false
so since when we're actually
doing evaluation we don't we're not
going to be doing backprop we don't
care about tracking the gradients so
this is kind of like a small performance
improvement we tell PyTorch that we
don't care about the gradients within here
so this second thing is maybe less important this will make your
code a little more efficient but even if
you forget it that's fine as long as you
don't accidentally like call backward on anything
but this net.eval() is really crucial
especially if you're doing things like dropout
otherwise your results are just not going to be correct
so now we have our predictions in the variable y
and remember since these are on gpu we
want to first convert them to cpu and
then we can call numpy to convert them
to numpy arrays
and we can see that it did pretty well
the last thing you'll do after training
and evaluation is probably uh you'll
want to save your model weights so that
later on you can use this trained model
to do something else
so the way that you save models in
PyTorch is that
you you basically take your parameters
and you store them in a dictionary that
gets serialized into some kind of file
so here we're specifying a path for a checkpoint
the convention is usually to uh make the
file extension.pt for PyTorch but
it's not a big deal you can call this
whatever you want
then we have torch.save() so if we call
net.state_dict() that gives us a dictionary
of not only the parameters of the
model but also anything else that's
important for making predictions for
example if you have a batch norm in your
model it's going to keep track of like
the running mean
so that's where state dict is slightly
different than parameters when you're
saving your model you don't just want
the parameters you want the entire state of the model
so we're going to be saving this dictionary to this path
and then let's say later on you come
back and you want to uh you want to load
this checkpoint um back into your model
and make predictions again
so what we'll do is we'll initialize a
new model uh make sure it has like the
same architecture as before and then
we'll call load_state_dict() and we're
going to pass in
the result of loading that file that we
saved to earlier
and then don't forget to call eval if
we're going to be doing this evaluation
so if you run this we can see that
let's see
oh i see okay well
all right let's just put them both on
gpu and now we can compare their parameters
and we'll see that
the loaded checkpoint has the exact
same names and parameters all the values
as the original model
to summarize what we did was we started
by training the model with our loss
function optimizer and the neural net that
we defined
making sure to move everything to gpu if
that's what we want to train on
we evaluated the model making sure to
set it to evaluation mode and turn off the gradients
and then finally we save the model ways
to some checkpoint file so that later on
we can load it and use it to make
predictions again