in the next part of today's lecture
I'm going to give you a kind of a
whirlwind tour
through different types of reinforcement learning algorithms
we'll talk about each of these types in
much more detail
in the next few lectures but for now
we'll just discuss what these types are
so they don't come as a surprise later
so the RL algorithms we'll cover will
generally be optimizing
the RL objective that I defined before
policy graded algorithms attempt to directly
calculate a derivative of this objective
with respect to theta
and then perform a grading descent
procedure using that derivative
value-based methods estimate value
functions or Q functions
for the optimal policy and then use
those value functions or Q functions
which are typically themselves
represented by a function approximately
like a neural network
to improve the policy oftentimes pure
value-based functions
don't even represent the policy directly
but rather represented implicitly
as something like an argmax of a Q function
Actor-critic methods are a kind of
hybrid between the two actor critic methods
Actor-critics methods
learn a Q function or value function and
then use it
to improve the policy typically by using
them to calculate a better policy gradient
and then model based reinforcement learning algorithms
will estimate a transition model
they'll estimate some model of the
transition probabilities t and then they
will either
use the transition model for planning
directly without any explicit policy
or use the transition model to improve
the policy
and there are actually many variants in
model based RL for how the transition
model can be used
all right let's start our conversation
with model-based RL algorithms
so for model-based RL algorithms
the green box will typically consist of
learning some model for p of S t+1
given St, at
so this could be a neural net that takes
in St, at
and either outputs a probability
distribution over t+1
or if it's a deterministic model just
attempts to predict S t+1 directly
and then the blue box has a number of different options
so let's focus in on that blue box since
model based RL algorithms will differ greatly
in terms of how they implement this part
So, one option for model based RL algorithms
is to simply use the learned model
directly to plan so you could
for example
learn how the rules of a chess game work
and then use your favorite discrete
planning algorithm like Monte Carlo tree search to play chess
or you can learn the physics of a
continuous environment for a robot
and then use some optimal control or
trajectory optimization procedure
through that learned physics model to
control the robot
another option is to use the learned model
to compute derivatives of the reward
function with respect to the policy
essentially through back propagation
this is a very simple idea but it
actually requires quite a few tricks to
make it work well
typically in order to account for
numerical stability so for example
second order methods tend to work a lot
better than first order methods for back
propagating the policy
another common use of a model is to use
the model to actually learn a separate
value function or Q function
and then use that value function or
Q function to improve the policy
so the value function or Q function
would be learned using some type of
dynamic programming method
and it's also fairly common to kind of
extend number three to essentially use a model
to generate additional data for a model
free reinforcement learning algorithm
and that can often work very well
alright, value function based algorithms
so for value function based algorithms
the green box involves fitting some estimate
of V(s) or Q(s,a)
usually using a neural network to
represent V(s) or Q(s,a)
where the network takes in s or
(s,a) as input and outputs a real
valued number
and then the blue box if it's a pure
value based method
would simply choose the policy to be the
argmax of
Q(s,a) so in a pure value based method
we wouldn't actually represent the policy
explicitly as a neural net
we would just represent it implicitly
as an argmax over a neural network
representing Q(s,a)
direct policy gradient method would
implement the blue box
simply by taking a gradient step or
gradient ascent step
on theta using the gradient of the
expected value of the reward
we'll talk about how this grading can be
estimated in the next lecture
but the green box for policy gradient algorithms
is very very simple
it just involves computing the total
reward along each trajectory
simply by adding up the rewards that
were obtained during the rollout
by the way when I use the term rollout
that simply means sample
of your policy it means run your policy
one step at a time and the reason we
call it a rollout
is because you're unrolling your policy
one step at a time
Actor-critic algorithms are a kind of
hybrid between value-based methods and
policy gradient methods
Actor-critic algorithms also fit a value
function or a Q function in the green box
just like value-based methods but then
in the blue box
they actually take a gradient ascend
step on the policy
just like policy gradient methods
utilizing the value function or Q function
to obtain a better estimate of the
gradient a more accurate gradient