hello and welcome to the fourth lecture of cs285
in today's lecture, we're going to go over a comprehensive introduction
to reinforce some learning algorithms definitions and basic concepts
so let's start with some definitions
first let's go over some of the terminology that we covered in
the previous lecture when we talked about imitation learning
we learned that we can represent a policy as a distribution over actions a_t condition on observations o_t
we call this policy pi and we often use a subscript theta to know the
policy depends on a vector of parameters that we're going to denote theta
when we're doing deep reinforcement learning oftentimes
we'll represent the policy with a deep neural network
although as we will learn in the next few lectures in the course
depending on the type of reinforcement learning algorithm
we might choose to represent the policy directly or
implicitly through some other object such as a value function
important definitions to know are the state which we denote st the observation
ot and the action a t as we learned in the imitation learning lecture.
the observation and state can be related to one another by the following graphical
model where the edge between observations and actions is the policy.
the edge between current states and actions and future states is the transition
probability or the dynamics and the state satisfies the markov property.
which means that the state at time t+1 is independent of the state at time t-1 when condition on the
current state st
the markov property is the main thing that distinguishes the state from the observation
the state has to satisfy the markov
property whereas the observation does not
and we learn in the imitation learning lecture that the observation is some stochastic function of the state which may or may not contain all the information necessary to infer the full state.
so that's kind of the primary difference
we will discuss algorithms for both fully observed reinforcement learning
where we have access to the state and partially observed reinforcement learning where you only have access to an observation
all right so that's the markov property
and typically you'll see me write the policy as π_θ(a_t /o_t) or π_θ(a_t / s_t)
depending on whether i'm talking about the partially observed or the fully observed case
i will sometimes get a little sloppy and use
st when in fact you could also use ot.
but in cases, where this distinction is
important i'll make a remark in the lectures
so in imitation learning we saw that we could collect a data set let's
say of humans driving a vehicle consisting of observation action tuples
and then use supervised learning algorithms to figure out how to
train a policy to take actions that resemble those of the expert
in today's lecture we'll introduce the formalism of reinforcement learning
which allows us to train these policies without having access to expert data
so to do that of course we need to define what it is that we want the policy to
do and we define the objective by means of something called a reward function
so we could say well which action is better or worse if you're driving this car if
you don't have any data how can you say what is a good action what is a bad action
so the reward function essentially tells you that the reward function
is a scalar valued function of the state and the action
although sometimes it can depend on only the state most
generally it can depend on both the state and the action
and it tells us which states and actions
are better
so for example if you're trying to drive a car you could say a state
where the car is driving quickly on the road is a high reward state
whereas a state where the car is collided
with another car is a low reward state
but crucially the objective in reinforcement learning is
not just to take actions that have high rewards right now
but rather to take actions that will
lead to higher awards later
so if you're driving on the road a little too fast you might be getting a high reward
but that might lead to an inevitable collision later that will lead to low reward
so you have to consider the future rewards when choosing the current actions and that's really at the heart of the decision decision making problem
that's at the heart of the reinforcement learning problems how do you
choose the right actions now to receive high rewards later.
together the state the action the reward and the transition probabilities define
what we call a markov decision process it is a decision process on a markovian state
so let's build up towards a full formal
definition of markov decision processes
we'll start with something called a markov chain.
the markov chain is named after andrei markov who was a mathematician
who pioneered the study of stochastic processes including markov chains
and the markov chain has a very simple definition it consists
of just two things a set of states s and a transition function t.
the state space is simply a set which
could be either discrete or continuous
so you could have a discrete state in which case
each state is a discrete element a finite size set
or you could have a continuous state in which case perhaps
your states correspond to real valued vectors in Rn.
t is a transition operator it can also be referred
to as a transition probability or a dynamics function
it specifies a conditional probability
distribution
so in a markov chain t denotes the probability of the
state at time t plus 1 condition on the state of time t
and the reason that it's called an operator is because if we
represent the probabilities of each state at time step t as a vector
so let's say we have n states this becomes a vector with n elements
and we can call it mu t comma i for the probability of the ith state
the whole vector would be called mu t then we can
write the the transition probabilities as a matrix
where the ijth entry is the probability of going
into state i if you're currently in the state j
and if we do this then we can express the vector of
state probabilities at the next time step mu t plus one
as simply a matrix vector product between the matrix of
probabilities t and the vector of state probabilities mu t
this is simply a way of writing the chain rule of
probability with a little bit of linear algebra.
but, here you can see that t acts on mu mu t as a linear
operator which is why we call the transition operator
it's an operator when applied to the current vector of state
probabilities produces the next vector of state probabilities
so here's the graphical model
corresponding to the markov chain
and here is the edge denoting transition
probabilities
and of course the states in the markov chain denote the states in the markov chain satisfy the markov property which means that the state at time t plus one is conditionally independent of the state at time t minus 1 given the state at time t
all right, now the markov chain by itself doesn't
allow us to specify a decision making problem
because there's no notion of actions
so in order to go towards the notion of actions,
we need to turn the markov chain into a markov decision process
and this was really a much more recent
invention pioneer than the 1950s.
so the markov decision process adds a few additional objects to
the markov chain it adds an action space and a reward function
so now we have a state space which is a discrete or continuous set of states.
we have an action space which is also a discrete or continuous set
so the graphical model now contains both states and actions and our transition probabilities
are now conditioned on both states and actions so we have p of st plus one given st comma a t
t is still called the transition operator but it can no
longer be expressed as a matrix now it's actually a tensor
because it has three dimensions the next
state the current state and the current action
but we can do the same kind of linear algebra trick so if we let
mu t comma j denote the probability of being in state j at time t
and we can have another vector that will
denote the probability of taking some action
and now we can write t as a tensor so t i j k is the probability
of entering state i if you're in state j and take action k.
then you can write a linear form that describes the state probability mu t plus one comma i at the next time step as a linear function of the current state probabilities the current action probabilities and the transition probabilities.
so that means that this transition operator although it is now a tensor is still a linear operator
that transforms current action and state probabilities into next time step state probabilities
now we also have this reward function and the reward function is a mapping
from the cartesian product of the state in action space into real value numbers
and this is what allows us to define
an objective for reinforcement learning
so we call r of st comma a_t the reward and our objective which i
will define a few slides from now will be to maximize total rewards
but before i do that, i just want to extend this markov decision
process definition to also define the partially observed markov decision
process and this is what will allow us to bring in the notion of observations
so a partially observed markov decision process further augments
the definition with two additional objects an observation space o
and an emission probability
or an observation probability e.
so again, s is the state space, a is an
action space and o is now an observation space
the graphical model now looks the same as it did for the mdp with the
addition that we have these observations o that depend on the state
so we have a transition operator just like before and now
we have an emission probability p(o_t / s_t).
of course we also have the reward
function
the reward function is still mapping from states and actions to real numbers
so this the reward function convention is the final states not on observations
but typically in a partially observed markov decision process or palmdp, we
would be making decisions based on observations without access to the true states
all right. now, that we've defined the mathematical objects of the markov chain
the markov decision process and the partially observed markov decision process
let's define an objective for
reinforcement learning
in reinforcement learning, we're going to be learning some object that defines
a policy so for now let's just assume that we learn the policy directly
and we'll see later on how there are some other
methods that might represent the policy implicitly
but for now we'll be explicitly learning pi theta (a/s).
we'll come back to the partial observed case later for
now let's just say that our policy is conditioned on s
and theta corresponds to the parameters of the policy
so if the policy is a deep neural net then theta
denotes the parameters of that deep neural net
the state goes into the policy, the action comes out and then the state and action go into the
transition probability basically the physics that govern the world which produces the next state
that's the process that we are controlling.
now in this process we can write down a
probability distribution over trajectories.
so trajectories are sequences of states and actions
s1a1 s2a2 etc etc until you get to state st at.
for now we will assume that our control problem is finite horizon which means that the
decision making task lasts for a fixed number of time steps capital t and then ends.
we will extend this to the infinite horizon setting shortly,
but for now we'll write down the finite horizon version
because it's quite a bit easier to uh to start with
so if we write down the joint distribution of our states and actions and here i'm putting the
subscript theta on this joint distribution to indicate that it depends on the policy pi theta
we can factorize it by using the chain rule in terms
of probability distributions that we've already defined
so we have an initial state distribution p of s1.
i sort of brush this under the rug when i define the markov chain the mdp and the palmdp. but all these also have an initial state distribution p of s1
and then we have a product over all time steps of the probability of an action (a_t/ s_t) and the probability of the transition to the next time step (s_t+1/s_t,a_t)
now i said this is derived from the
chain rule of probability
but of course in the chain rule of probability
you need to condition on all past variables
but here we are exploiting the markov property to
drop the dependence on st minus 1 st minus 2 etc etc
because we know that st plus 1 is conditionally
independent of st minus 1 given st
so this is how we can
define the tree distribution
and for notational brevity i will sometimes
write p of tau to denote p of s1 through s_t, a_t
so tau is just a shorthand for trajectory and
all it means is a sequence of states and actions
so having defined the trajectory distribution, we can actually define an objective for reinforcement learning
and we can define that objective as an and we can define that objective as an under the trajectory distribution
so the goal in reinforcement learning is to
find the parameters theta that define our policy
so as to maximize the expected value
of the sum of rewards over the trajectory
so we would like a policy that produces trajectories
that have the highest possible rewards in expectation
and the expectation of course accounts for the uh stochasticity of the
policy the transition probabilities and the initial state distribution
so this is the definition of the reinforced
learning objective that we're going to work with
there are of course a few variants on this and we'll derive them over
the course of the next few lectures this is the most basic version.
so at this point, i would like all of you to pause and look
carefully at the subjective and really make sure that you understand what this means
that you understand what it means to have a sum of rewards,
what it means to take their expectation under a trajectory distribution
what a trajectory distribution is and how it is influenced by our choice
of policy parameters theta which in turn influence the policy pi theta
because if this part is unclear then what follows in the
remainder of this lecture will be quite hard to follow
so please take a moment to think about this and if you have any questions about
the trajectory distribution please be sure to write a comment on the video
all right. let's proceed.
so, one of the things that we might notice about this factorization of the structure distribution is that
it actually although it's a it's defined in terms of the objects that we had in the markov decision process
it can also be interpreted as a markov
chain
and to interpret this as a markov chain,
we need to define a kind of augmented state space.
so our original state space is s but we also have these
actions and the actions make this a markov decision process
but we know that the action depends on the state based on the policy so pi theta
a t given s t allows us to get a distribution of our actions conditioned on states
so we can do is we can group the state in
action together into a kind of augmented state.
and now,  the augmented
states actually form a markov chain
so p of s t plus one comma a t plus one given s t comma a t the transition operator in this
augmented markov chain is simply the product of the transition operator in the mdp and the policy
so this can allow us to define the objective in a slightly different
way that will be convenient to use in some of our later derivations
so far, i've defined the objective as an expected value
under the trajectory distribution of the sum of rewards
but remember that our distribution actually
follows a markov chain with this augmented space
and this transition operator is the product
of the mdp transitions and the policy
so we could also write the objective by linearity of expectation as the sum over time of the
expected values under the state actual marginal in this markov chain of the reward of that time step.
so this is just using linearity of expectation to take the sum out of the
expectation so that you have a sum over t of the expectation over tau of r s_t a_t
and then since the thing inside the expectation not only depends
on s_t a_t, we can marginalize all the other variables out
and we are left with a sum over the expectation
under p theta s t comma a t of r s t a t
now this might seem like kind of a useless little mathematical
you know kind of rewriting of the original objective.
but it turns out to be quite useful if we want
to extend this to the infinite horizon case
so this marginal p theta s t given a t in a finite time markov chain
can be obtained just by marginalizing out all the other time steps
but we can also use this objective to
get the infinite horizon case
so what if t equals infinity?
the first thing that happens if t equals infinity
is your objective might become ill-defined.
for example, if your reward your reward is always positive then you have a
sum of an infinite number of positive numbers which is going to be infinity.
so we need some way to make the objective finite and there are a few ways of doing this one way of doing is well which i'll
use now for convenience but is actually not the most common way is to use what's called the average reward formulation.
so you basically take this sum of expected
rewards and you divide it by capital t
so basically the average reward overall time steps dividing by capital
capital, t is a constant in general, this doesn't change the maximum
but then you can take t to infinity and get a well-defined quantity later on we'll learn about
something called discounts which is another way to get a finite number for the infinite horizon case.
but, making this finite is pretty easy.
let's talk about how we can actually
define an infinite horizon objective.
so we have our markov chain from before and our augmented markov chain has this transition operator so that means
that we can write the vector st plus one comma a t plus one as some linear operator t applied to st comma a t.
and this is the state action
transition operator
and more generally, we can skip k time steps ahead and we can say
that s_t+k, a_t+k is equal to t to the power k times s_t, a_t.
so one question we could ask is does the state action marginal p of s t comma a t converge to a
stationary distribution basically converge to a single distribution as little k goes to infinity
if this is true that means that we should be able to write
the stationary distribution mu as being equal to t times mu
and under a few technical assumptions namely ergodicity and the chain
being aperiodic we can actually show the stationary distribution exists.
intuitively being a periodic simply means exactly what it sounds like that the markov chain is not periodic and being ergotic means that roughly speaking every state can be reached from every other state with non-zero probability.
the ergotic assumption is important because it prevents a situation where
if you start in one part of the mdp you might never reach another one
so if this is true if starting in one part may result in you
never reaching another part then where you start always matters
and the stationary distribution doesn't exist
but if this is not the case if there's even a slight chance of getting
to any state from any other state eventually then you will have a stationary distribution provided as a periodic
so the station distribution must obey this equation mu equals
t times mu because otherwise it's not a stationary distribution
so stationary means it's the same before and after the transition and if it's the same before
and after the transition then applying t enough times will eventually allow you to reach it
you can solve for the station distribution uh simply by rearranging this equation to see that
it is equal to tau minus i times so they can be written as tau minus i times mu equals 0.
and remember that mu is a distribution so it's a
vector of numbers that are all positive and sum to 1.
so one way you can find mu is by finding the eigenvector
with eigenvalue one for the matrix defined by t
so mu is eigenvector of t with
eigenvalue one
and it always exists under the
ergodicity and aperiodicity assumptions
so if we know that if we run this markov chain forward enough
times, eventually it'll settle into mu, that means that as t goes to infinity,
this sum over the expectations of the marginals
becomes dominated by the stationary distribution terms
so you have some finite number of terms initially that are not in the stationary distribution mu1 mu2 mu3 etc. then you have
infinitely many terms that are very very close to the stationary distribution
which means that once you put in the average reward case so you're going to find put a 1 over t.
and then take the limit as t goes to infinity, the limit is basically going
to be the expected value of the reward under the stationary distribution
and that allows us to define an objective for reinforcement
learning in the infinite horizon case as t goes to infinity
this is perhaps a lot to take in so this would be a good place to pause think about the derivation on this
slide and if something is unclear or you have any questions please be sure to write them in the comments
now, one last bit that i want to describe in this section which is very important for understanding the basic principle behind a lot of reinforcement learning methods is that reinforcement learning is really about optimizing expectations
so although we talk about reinforcement learning in terms of choosing actions that
lead to high rewards we're always really concerned about expected values of rewards
and the interesting thing about expected values is that expected values can be continuous in the parameters of the
corresponding distributions even when the function that we're taking the expectation of is itself highly discontinuous
and this is a really important fact for understanding why reinforced learning algorithms can use smooth optimization methods like
gradient descent to optimize objectives that are seemingly non-differentiable like binary rewards for winning or losing a game
let me explain this with a little toy
example.
let's imagine that you're driving down a mountain road and your reward is plus one
if you stay on the road and zero if you fall or negative one if you fall off the road
so the reward function here appears to be discontinuous.
there is a discontinuity between staying
on the road and falling off the road,
and if you try to optimize the reward function with respect to for
example the position of the car,
that optimization problem can't really be solved with gradient based methods, because the reward is not a continuous or much less a differentiable function of the car's position
however if you have a probability distribution over some action, let's
say that abstractly that you just get to choose like fall or don't fall
so you have a binary action the other fall you don't fall and it's a bernoulli random variable with
parameter theta so with probability theta you fall off with probability one minus theta you don't fall off
now the interesting thing is that the expected value of the
reward with respect to pi theta is actually smooth in theta
because you have a probability of theta falling off which has a reward
of minus one and a probability of one minus theta staying on the road
so the reward is one minus theta plus one minus theta minus theta
and that's perfectly smooth and perfectly differentiable in theta
so this is this is a very important property that will come up again and again and that really explains
why reinforcement algorithms can optimize seemingly non-smooth and even sparse reward functions,
which is that expected values of non-smooth and non-differentiable functions under differentiable and smooth probability distributions are themselves smooth and differentiable
okay let's pause there