all right in the next portion of this lecture
i'm going to introduce the notion of value functions
which are a very useful mathematical object
both for designing reinforcement learning algorithms
and for conceptually thinking about the reinforcement learning objective
so as i mentioned earlier
the reinforcement objective can be defined as an expectation
it's an expectation of a sum of rewards
with respect to the trajectory distribution
or equivalently a sum over time of the expected reward
for every state action marginal
now one of the things we could do with this expectation is we can actually write it out recursively
so you know how we can apply the chain rule of probability to factorize the
trajectory distribution as a product of many distributions
in the same way we can apply the chain rule and write out an expected value with respect to that distribution
as a series of nested expectations
so the outermost expectation here would be over p of s1
inside of it we have an expected value with respect to a1
distributed according to pi of a1 given s1
and now since we have an expectation for both s1 and a1
we can put in the first reward r of s1 comma a1
and notice that this inner expectation the one over a1 is conditioned on s1
i have a bunch of blank space here
because i'm going to need to put in all the other rewards
but we already have r of s1a1
now we add to that all the other rewards
but those require
putting in another expectation now over
s2 distributed query to p of s2 given s1 a1
so this expectation is conditioned on s1 a1
and inside of that
we have another expectation over a2
distribute according to pi of a2 given s2
and now since we have both s2 and a2 we can put in r of s2 a2
and then we add to that the expected value over s3
inside of which is the expected value over a3
inside of it is r of s3 a3 and so on and so on
and we have this these nested expectations
now at first it kind of seems like we just wrote a very concise
expected value of trajectories as a really really messy set of nested expectations
but one thing that we could think about is well
what if we had some some function that told us
the stuff that goes inside of the x of the second expectation
what if we had some function that tells us r of s1 plus comma a1 plus the expected value over s2 plus etc etc
so what if we we knew this part
so let's uh define a symbol for this let's say that q of s1 comma a1
is equal to r of s1 comma a1 plus the expectation over s2 of the expectation over a2 of r of s28 to ETC
so basically just this middle part
the part that goes inside the second set of square brackets
i'm just going to call that q of s1 comma a1
then we can write our original rl objective as simply the expected value
over s1 of the expected value over a1 of q of s1 comma a1
so it's just a little bit of symbolic manipulation a little bit of definition
but the important point about this definition is that
if you knew q of s1 comma a1 then optimizing the policy at the first
time step would be very easy
so if you had access to a queue of s1 comma a1
and you needed to select the policy pi of a1 given s1
you would just select the policy for which this expected value is largest
you could simply test every action and just
assign 100 probability to the best one one with the largest value for q
so this basic idea can be extended to a more general concept
so this is this is the simple rule
that i said you know a simple way to get
pi here is just assign a probability of one to the arc max
so the the more general principle is
what we're going to call the q function
so the q function can be defined at other time steps not just time step one
and the definition is this
q pi of st comma a t and i say q pi because it depends on pi
q pi of st comma 80 is equal to the sum over all time steps from t
until the end capital t of the expected value
of the reward at that future time step
condition on starting an st comma at.
so what that means is basically if you
start an st comma at and then roll out your policy
for the rest of time will be the expected sum of rewards
a closely related quantity that we can also define is something called the value function
the value function is defined in much the same way only it's conditioned
only a state rather than a state in action
so the value function says if you start in state st
and then roll out your policy what will
be your expected total value
and the value function can also be written
as the expected value over actions of the q function
because if the q function tells you they expect the total reward
if you start an st comma a t then taking the expectation of that with respect to a t
will give you the expected total reward if you start an st
so now one observation we could make is the expectation of the value function
at state s1 is the entirety of the reinforcement learning objective
for the same reason that the expected value with respect to s1a1 of q s1a1
was the rl objective on the previous slide
okay so at this point i would like everyone to pause for a minute
and think about these definitions of q functions and value functions
you might want to flip back to the previous slide if something here is unclear
take a moment to think about that and
if something about these definitions is unclear please make sure to write a question in the comments
all right let's continue
so what are q functions and value functions good for
well i provided some intuition for this a couple slides ago
when i talked about how once you have a q function
for at least the first time step
you can recover a better policy for the first time step
so one idea is that if we have a policy pi
and if we can figure out its full q function q pi s comma a
then we can improve pi
for example we can pick a new policy pi prime that assigns a probability of 1
to a given action if that action is the
r max of q pi s a
and we can do this on not just the first time step
but on all of the time steps and in fact
we can show that this policy is at least as good as pi
and probably better
don't worry if it's not obvious to you right now why this is true
we'll cover this in much more detail later
but this is the basis of a class of methods called policy iteration algorithms
which themselves can be used to derive q-learning algorithms
and crucially it doesn't matter what pi is you can always improve it in this way
another idea which we will use in the next lecture when we talk about policy gradients
is you can use this to compute a gradient
to increase the probability of a good action a
so the intuition is that if q pi s a is larger than v of s
then a is better than average
because remember that the v pi of s is just the expected value of q pi s a under pi of a given s
by this definition v pi of s is how you will do on average
when you use your policy from state s
so if you can do better than average
if you can choose an action a
so that q pi s a is larger than v pi of s
then you will do better you'll do better than average
under your old policy so one thing you
could do is you could modify
pi of a given s to increase the probability of actions
whose value under the q function is larger
than the value at that state
and you can actually use this to get a gradient based update rule on pi
these ideas are very important in rl
and we'll revisit them again and again in the next few lectures
when we talk about model free reinforcement learning algorithms
all right so in the anatomy of the reinforcement learning algorithm
the green box is typically where you would use or where you would learn
q functions or value functions
so q functions and value functions fundamentally are objects that evaluate
how good your policy currently is
so you would typically fit them or learn them in the green box
and then use them in the blue box to improve the policy