okay so we saw that we can address the
distributional shift problem
using the dagger algorithm but the
dagger algorithm does have a few
practical
challenges that make it a little tricky
to use because of this additional
labeling step
can we make deep imitation learning work
without having to collect
more data so dagger addresses the
problem of distributional
shift or drift but what if our model is
so good
that it doesn't have this drifting
problem what if it's so accurate
that it doesn't deviate far enough
from p data to ot and still stays good
well in order to do that we need to
mimic the x-ray behavior very accurately
but we have to also make sure that we
don't overfit in practice there are a
few things we can do to facilitate this
that can actually work empirically
although they do not have the
theoretical guarantees the dagger has
to try to understand what we can do we
could first ask
why might we fail to fit the expert data
why might our model not be perfect
there are a few possible reasons one
reason is that
even if the observation is fully
markovian meaning that the observation
is enough to perfectly ignore infer the
state
the humans behavior might still be
non-markovian
a second possibility is that if we have
continuous actions
the demonstrator's behavior might be
multimodal
meaning that they might
inconsistently select from among
multiple different
modes in the distribution making it hard
to imitate
let's start with the first problem
so typically we would learn a
markovian policy that's a jargon that
means that our policy depends only on ot
not an ot minus one or ot minus two
and a person might not actually act this
way so
being markovian basically means if we
see the same thing twice
we do the same thing twice regardless of
what happened before
in some cases humans do behave this way
but in many cases they don't so if
you're driving a car
and you just had someone cut you off
you're a little bit
kind of shaken maybe you're a little
anxious
you'll react a little differently to
whatever happens next than if that
person hadn't done that
more generally humans are just not very
consistent
and whatever strategy you're using to
control
the system might be non-markovian
even if there exists an optimal
markovian strategy
so it's often very unnatural for human
demonstrators to be
perfect markovian experts to take the
same actions
in the same state if they see the same
state twice
so maybe a person acts more like this
maybe they they actually have a
distribution over actions
condition o1 through ot conditioning the
entire history of observations
and of course if this is how your expert
is behaving then you won't be able to
reproduce their behavior perfectly
without any markovian policy
now we could use the whole history in
imitation
so instead of just conditioning our
model the current image that the car is
observing we can condition on the entire
history of images
there are a few practical challenges
with this though first
if we simply concatenate all the images
together we might have a variable number
of images depending on how long our
history is and it's
not obvious how to input that into a
standard convolutional neural network
and also if the number of images is
large we might end up with too many
weights
so a common solution to this issue
is to employ some kind of recurrent
network one very popular architecture
for this
is to use a convolutional encoder a
convolutional neural network
that reads in the image and turns that
image into
a RNN state and then we have a
recurrent neural network
a recurrent neural network backbone that
encodes
an arbitrary length sequence of these
encodings
into the current state which is then
used to produce the action
now in practice we would typically use
something like a LSTM cell
for actually representing this RNN we're
not going to cover neural network
architectures in great detail in this
course
so if you want to learn about RNNs and
LSTM cells
i would encourage you to do a little bit
of your own reading the main point that
i want to make is that these kind of
LSTM
or RNN type architectures can greatly
mitigate the non-markovian problem
so typically we would have shared
weights for a combat encoder and then
have a RNN
all right now one little aside that I
want to mention briefly is
you know in general this RNN approach
would mitigate the non-markovian policy
issue
but there are some reasons why it might
also work poorly
so to illustrate a potential issue
with an imitation learning in general
but that might
be especially important when dealing
with histories let's consider the
following
scenario let's say that you are
driving the car and you have a camera
that's inside the car so the camera can
see out the front windshield
and it also sees the dashboard and this
car has a funny brake indicator on the
dashboard I know most cars don't have
this but let's say that it does so every
time you step on the brake
there's a little light that lights up on
the dashboard
now if there's a person standing in the
road you really need to press on the
brake
and let's say that your data contains
these kinds of examples
but in all those examples when you hit
the brake
the light on the dashboard lights up and
there's a person in front of the car
so now your neural network model has to
figure out
is the braking caused by the presence of
a person
or by the light going off and it's very
easy for the neural network to associate
the light with the brake
because the light always turns on when
you're stepping on the brake
it's a very consistent cue whereas the
person standing in front of the car
is a little more complicated to figure
out
if the brake light was obscured if
information was removed from the
observation
then this issue would go away so we have
kind of a funny conundrum here we're
adding more observation
adding this brake light actually makes
imitation learning harder
because it creates a kind of causal
confusion problem it creates a situation
where
the cause and effect relationship
between parts of your observation and
your actions
become difficult to deduce from just the
data so the braking was caused by the
presence of the person
and the light went off because of the
braking but the model might not be able
to understand this I might instead
conclude that the braking
should be caused by the light
so if you want to learn more about this
phenomena there's a paper by pim dahan
called causal confusion and imitation
learning
now this is not specific to
markovian or non-markovian policies this
can happen in all sorts of invitation
learning scenarios
but two questions that I might ask you
to ponder a question one
does including history make it causal confusion
or make it worse I'd encourage you to
think about this question
and consider writing your answer in the
comments
question two can dagger mitigate causal
confusion so if you use dagger
will that fix this issue and if so why
so I won't give you the answer this in
the lecture but
we could discuss this more in the
discussion section
okay so that's non-markovian behavior
now let's talk about the other potential
reason
why we might fail to perfectly fit the
expert behavior
which is multimodal behavior so
let's say that you're flying that drone
in that video
and you need to fly around a tree and
maybe the human expert
sometimes flies around the tree going
left and sometimes flies around the tree
going right
now if your actions are discrete if you
just have a discrete left action right
action and straight action
this is not a problem because a soft max
distribution
of the sort that we typically use when
we want neural networks
to output categorical distributions
could easily capture the notion
that the left action has high
probability and the right action has
high probability
but the straight action is low
probability so that's not a problem
but if we have continuous actions then
we would typically
parametrize the output distribution as a
multivariate normal distribution a
gaussian
determined by its mean and variance
now if you just get to pick one mean and
one variance how do you put that mean
and variance
to model the fact that you can go left
and you can go right we should never go
straight
that causes a big problem right because
essentially
you average together the possibilities
and you get exactly the wrong thing you
get exactly the behavior going straight
because that's the average between left
and right so this is why multimodal
behavior can cause problems
but in general humans do tend to be
multimodal humans tend to
exhibit very complicated distributions
in their demonstrations
unless they're performing very simple
tasks and without continuous actions that
can be a big
problem so there are a few possible
solutions
one solution is not to use
a single gaussian output distribution
instead of outputting the parameters of
one gaussian a mean and a variance
you can instead output a mixture of
gaussians multiple means and multiple
variances
which could capture multiple modes you
could also use a latent variable model
which is a more sophisticated way to
represent
a complex probability distribution in
continuous spaces
and you could also do what's called
autoregressive discretization
so I'll talk about each of these three
next
first let's talk about mixtures of
gaussians these are sometimes called
mixture density networks so the idea is
that
instead of outputting mu and sigma the
mean and variance of one gaussian
you output n mu's and n sigmas
and also nws and then the probability of
a given o
is given by a gaussian mixture a sum
over each of those
n of wi times a gaussian with mean ui
and covariance sigma i
so it's a very simple approach now
some of the trade-offs with gaussian
mixture
mixture models for this are that you
need more output parameters
and
the ability to model multimodal
distributions in very high dimensions
can be challenging so the higher the
dimensionality is the more mixture
elements you need
and in general for arbitrary
distributions the number of mixture
elements needed to model them well
in theory increases exponentially with
dimensionality so
if you're controlling the gas and brake
and steering of a car that's just two
dimensions
that's not a problem but if you're
controlling all of the joints of a
humanoid robot which might be hundreds
or all the prices of all the products on
amazon which might be millions
then gaussian mixtures might not be such
a good choice
a more sophisticated but more difficult
to implement
option is a latent variable model so in
a latent variable model
the output distribution is gaussian
still
but in addition to inputting the image
we also input
a latent variable into our model which
might be drawn from some prior
distribution
so essentially our model takes in an
image and some noise
and turns that image and noise into a
gaussian distribution of reactions
for different noise inputs it might
produce different gaussian distributions
and in theory you can actually show that
such a model can represent
arbitrary distributions however training
such a
model can be a little tricky so I'm not
going to go into detail about the math
of how to train these latent variable
models
although we will have a lecture on
something called variational
autoencoders
towards the second half of the class but
for now if you're interested in latent
variable models
consider looking up conditional
variational autoencoders
normalizing flows or stein variational
gradient descent
the last option I'll cover which i think
strikes a good balance
between simplicity and expressivity is
autoregressive discretization
so a mixture of gaussians is very simple
but has difficulty with very complex
distributions
a latent variable model is very
expressive but more complex to implement
another regressive discretization is
perhaps a nice middle ground between the
two
it can represent arbitrary distributions
but in my opinion it's quite a bit
easier to use
than latent variable models so the idea
in auto regressive discretization is
the following remember how if we have
discrete actions
this multimodality problem is not an
issue because of discrete actions
a soft max categorical distribution can
easily represent any distribution
however if you have continuous actions
discretizing them can be challenging
because in general the number of bins
that you need for discretizing an
n-dimensional action space is
exponential in n
so if you have only two action
dimensions like steering and gas and
brake
that's easy to do but if you have many
more dimensions this quickly becomes
impractical
autoregressive discretization
discretizes one dimension at a time
but can still represent arbitrary
distributions by using a club
a clever neural network trick
so first we will discretize the first
dimension of the action so we'll have a
neural net that takes in the image
and outputs a discretization
of the first action dimension
then we will sample from the softmax
and then we'll have a value for the
first action dimension
and then we'll feed this value into
another neural net that's going to
output a distribution
over the second action dimension we'll
sample that and repeat
so we discretize one dimension at a time
which means that we never need to incur
that exponential cost
but because we're modeling the
distribution over the next dimension
condition on the previous one
then by the chain rule of probability we
can actually represent a full joint
distribution
over all of the action dimensions so
this is an easy trick to implement
and it actually ends up being quite
powerful in practice
okay so to recap we talked about how
just imitation learning by itself is
just behavioral cloning by itself is
often but not always
insufficient because of the distribution
mismatch problem
but sometimes it works well it can work
well for instance
as in that example with the nvidia paper
where we use some trick to stabilize the
system
or more generally if our samples come
from a stable trajectory distribution
or if we add some additional on policy
data for instance using dagger
but also we can do a wide range of
different tricks we can add a wide range
of different tricks
to improve our model so that it fits the
data much more accurately
and while this in theory doesn't
alleviate the distributional shift
problem
in practice it can actually make even
naive behavior cloning work
if we're careful about tricks for
handling non-markovian
policies and for handling multimodality