in general the answer is no and to give you a little bit of intuition
for why behavioral cloning might go wrong even while regular supervised learning would work
uh let's uh start with a very kind of abstract picture of a control problem
so i'll draw a lot of pictures like this in today's lecture
when i draw a picture like this  the axis on the left represents the state
now of course in general the state is not one-dimensional
but i'll have this axis be one-dimensional so that it's easier to visualize
and then the other axis represents time
so this black curve represents the trajectory through time at every point in time
there's a different value of the state
and let's say that this black trajectory represents our training data
so we're going to take this as our training data use it to train a policy
that goes from s to a and then we'll run that policy
so now in red i'm going to draw what this policy will do when we run it
initially the policy stays pretty close to the training data
because we're going to use a large neural network and will train it very well
but it does make some small mistakes
every learned model will make at least some small mistakes this is basically inevitable
the trouble is that when this model makes some small mistake
it will find itself in a state that's just a little bit different
than the states that it was trained on
and when it finds itself in a state that is unusual that is different from the training states
it'll make a bigger mistake because it doesn't quite know what to do there
and as these mistakes compound the state becomes more and more different
and the mistakes get bigger and bigger
until after a while the learned policy might end up doing something very different
from the demonstrated behavior
so you could imagine the car scenario
the car will veer a little to the left just a tiny bit
then see something unfamiliar and here
to the left a little more until eventually goes off the road
and we'll see we'll discard describe this phenomenon much more formally later on in in the lecture
but does this work in practice well
in practice actually sometimes it's pretty effective
so these videos are collected from a paper uh released by nvidia in 2016
and you can see that initially they had a lot of trouble with the system
it would kind of go off the road do some messy things run into cones
but after collecting a lot of data and using a few little tricks
they actually ended up with a system
that did something fairly sensible
that could autonomously drive between the cones
stay on the road and exhibit some you know fairly reasonable behavior
so why is that why is it that we can use behavioral cloning methods in practice
to train policies that actually do something fairly decent well
we'll discuss this in more detail in part two
but one of the things that i want to mention briefly now is
the particular technique that was used to address this issue in this paper by nvidia
so if we look at the paper and we look at the their description of their system
it mostly looks very much like what we expect so the there is a conv-net
the conv-net produces a steering angle
the you know the the car tracks that steering angle the conv-net takes this input
camera inputs but something that you might notice here is that
there's a center camera left camera and right camera
well it turns out that one of the tricks
that was used in this paper which turns out to be kind of important
is that you record three different camera images at the same time
one pointing forward one left and one right
the forward image is supervised with whatever steering angle the person had
the image looking to the left is supervised of the steering angle
that is a little bit to the right of what the person did
so that means that if the car saw an image that was going left off the road
it should steer to the right
and correspondingly the image pointed to
the right is supervised with a term to the left
now you can imagine how this particular trick in the special case of driving a car
would actually mitigate this drifting problem
because now these left and right images
are essentially teaching the policy how to correct little mistakes
and if i can correct those mistakes
then maybe they won't accumulate as much
now this is a special case of a more general principle
the more general principle is that while errors in the trajectory will compound
if you can somehow modify your training data
so that your training data illustrates little mistakes and
feedbacks to correct those mistakes
then perhaps the policy can learn those feedbacks and stabilize
and there are a number of different ways to do this some of them will discuss later on in the course
for example if you train a stable optimal feedback controller around the demonstration
and use that feedback controller as supervision you can actually get stable policies
that inherit that stability
or you can simply ask a person to potentially make mistakes and correct those mistakes
so there are little tricks like this
that we can use to try to patch the issue
but something that we could ask
also to derive a more general solution
is what's the kind of the underlying mathematical principle behind this drift
what's really going on here
well when we run the policy
we're sampling from pi theta a t given ot
and this distribution pi theta a t given ot
it was trained on some data distribution
and that data distribution we'll call it p data ot
this is basically the distribution of observations
seen in our training data
now we know from supervised learning theory that
when you train a particular model on a particular training distribution
and you get good training error and you don't over fit
fthen you would expect to also get good test error
if test points are drawn from the same distribution
so if we see new observations
that come from the same distribution as our training data
even if the observations themselves are not the same
we would expect our learned policy to produce the right action on those observations
however when we run our policy
the distribution over observations that we actually see is different
the observation over the the distribution of observations is different
because the policy takes different actions
which result in different observations
so after a while p pi theta o t
becomes very different from p data ot
and this is the reason for this compounding error problem
so can we somehow fix this can we make p data ot
equal to p pi theta ot if we could do this
then we know that our policy would produce good actions
simply from standard results in supervised learning theory
now one way to make p data ot equal to p pi theta ot
is to simply make the policy perfect
if the policy is perfect and it never makes mistakes
then these distributions will match
but that's of course very very hard
so what if instead of being clever about our policy
we're actually we can try to actually be clever about our data distribution
so let's maybe not change the policy in some clever way
but let's actually change our data to avoid this distributional shift problem
that's the basic idea behind a method called dagger
dagger stands for "Dataset Aggregation"
so in dagger, our goal is to collect training data
that comes from p pi theta ot instead of p data ot
because if we have observation action tuples
from p pi theta o t and we train on those observation action tuples
then the distributional shift problem will be gone
so here's how dagger accomplishes this
we're going to actually run
pi theta a t given ot
which will produce samples from p by theta ot
and then we'll request additional labels at those observations
so step one is to initialize our policy
by training on the human dataset
then we're going to run our policy to
collect an additional data set of observations
that i'm denoting here as d pi and
these observations now come from p by theta o t
then we'll ask a human to label all of these observations with optimal actions
so someone will literally watch the observations that the machine produced
and tell the machine what the optimal action
that they would have taken for those observations actually is
and then we will aggregate
we will actually merge these data sets
and then train the policy on it again
now when we train the policy again on this merged data set
the policy will change
which means that even though our observations in d pi came from p pi theta
now theta is different and p by theta is also different
so we have to repeat this process
but we can actually show and this is shown in the paper by ross at all
that introduced this algorithm that repeating this process enough times
eventually does extra converge
resulting in a final data set that does come from the same distribution as the policy asymptotically
so here's an example of a policy trained with dagger
flying a drone through a forest
this policy doesn't actually use a deep neural network
it actually uses some linear image features
but subsequent work has done this with deep neural networks as well
so this drone initially was not able to deflect far forest very well
but after a few iterations of soliciting additional labels from the human
it was able to navigate the forest quite proficiently
so what is the issue with dagger
why don't we always use this algorithm in invitation learning (imitaition?)
well a lot of the issues with dagger really come from step three
it's a little bit problem dependent
but in many cases asking a human to manually label dpi with optimal actions
can actually be quite onerous
imagine doing this yourself
imagine that you're watching a video of a drone flying through a forest
and you have to steer that drone provide optimal actions
without your actions actually affecting the drone in real time
that's very unnatural to humans because
humans don't just map observations to actions in open loop
we actually do feedback control
we watch the effect of our actions and compensate accordingly
when you can't see the effect of your actions
it can be a little hard to do this
so this is of course situational
in some domains providing optimal
actions for arbitrary observations
can be reasonably straightforward such
as an abstract decision making problems
like for example if you're doing
operations research inventory management
et cetera
it's easy to ask an expert you know if
your warehouse is in this state and your
prices are this
how should you change the prices but
it's comparatively much hard ask a human
if you see this image how should you
turn the steering wheel
all right