So, why should we care about deep reinforcement learning?
In particular deep is in the title of this class
So, let's talk about that a little bit.
And to start this conversation,
we'll start with a really big question.
and this is a question that we'll come back
to a few times in the first lecture module.
How do we build intelligent machines?
and by this, i really mean literally
what it says on at the top
intelligent machines the kind of machines that we see in cartoons
are robot butlers robot helpers that
help with medical care
or even science fiction robots that
pilot starships
or if you're a little bit more
mischievously inclined
evil robot villains.
Intelligent machines have to be able to
adapt they have to handle
flexibly the complexity and
unpredictability of the real world.
If we wanted to build for instance an
autonomous oil tanker
that would not be very difficult to do
today.
While it's hard for humans to
figure out
how to navigate the ocean to reach a
destination half a world away
a combination of gps and motion planning
can actually solve this problem
reasonably well.
However, most oil tankers still have
human crews on board.
Why is that? Well, it's because when
something goes wrong when something
breaks in the engine room,
you really need a person to go down
there and fix it.
While navigating the oil tanker
is comparatively not a very difficult
artificial intelligence problem.
Fixing something when it goes wrong with
current technology is exceedingly difficult
The difficulty really comes from the
fact the real world is unstructured and
unpredictable.
And a very powerful technology for
handling the unstructured unpredictable
nature of the real world that we have at
our disposal is deep learning.
In deep learning, we train a very large
heavily over parametrized model like a
deep neural network to map inputs to outputs.
For instance, if you want to recognize
objects in an image
you would collect a large number of
labeled images and then
use typically standard supervised
learning methods to predict inputs from outputs.
But deep learning is fundamentally about
the choice of large over-parameterized models
more than it is about the choice of the algorithm.
We've seen deep learning methods
succeed at tasks ranging from
image classification to translating text
even directly from images to recognizing human speech.
And these are all open world settings in
the sense that
you need models that generalize
effectively to things they've never seen before
and all sorts of weird special cases and
unusual situations can arise.
Reinforcement learning provides a
formalism for behavior as i mentioned
before it provides a mathematical
way of thinking about sequential decision-making.
In reinforcement learning,
an agent interacts with the world,
gets observations and rewards
and these kinds of methods have been
used in combination
with deep neural networks for a variety
of
applications where you do have to handle
flexibly
unusual and unpredictable situations.
For instance, one of the early successes
of the combination of reinforcement
learning and neural networks has been
learning to play
the board game of backgammon.
This is a system called td gammon
that learned to play backgammon at the
level of an expert human.
Not quite at the level of beating
the championed human player but a very
at a very professional level.
The technology behind alphago which
defeated the human champion for go 2016
in many ways had a lot in common with
td gammon back in the 90s.
Deep reinforcement learning methods
meaning reinforcement learning algorithms
that use deep neural networks have been
used for tasks ranging from
robotic locomotion to robotic
manipulation skills
playing video games and so on.
So what is deep RL exactly?
And why should we care about it?
Well, to understand the importance of
deep RL the difference that it makes in
reinforcement learning methods
Let's start with
an example from a different domain an
example from computer vision
to see why it is that deep neural
networks
have such a transformative effect on the
capabilities of machine learning systems.
So if we go back in time maybe about
15 to 20 years
and see how computer vision was
typically done we would see something
like this.
You start with pixels in an image and
then you extract some hand-designed
low-level visual features from those
pixels like for instance a histogram of
oriented gradients.
Then you might extract some mid-level features,
like a deformable parts model,
for example,
and then on top of those mid-level features
you would train some simple
linear classifier
like a support vector machine to
actually classify the thing that you want.
Now with deep learning the deep neural net
performs much the same function
internally it has mid-level features and
low level features
and a classifier the difference is that
these now don't have to be designed by hand.
They're actually learned end-to-end by
the deep neural network.
This not only means that we save a lot
of human effort in designing all those
features.
But it also means that the features are
optimally adapted to the tasks that they
actually have to solve.
So you don't just get some generic
histogram or ingredients features you
get the right features
for classifying tigers from jaguars.
Now let's think about how this lesson
maps on to
the reinforcement learning setting.
Let's think about the game of backgammon.
If you wanted to use standard
reinforcement learning methods you would
have to extract features from the game
of backgammon somehow.
What kind of features do you use?
Well, maybe if you're an extra backgammon
player you might know that there are
some things that matter in the game i
i'm not an expert backgammon player so i
don't know what those things are but
perhaps you know what they are and then
you could
write them down.
But it's not enough to just have
features that you think are important
for the game they have to also be
features
that can be used to represent policies
value functions and other objects
relevant to reinforcement learning in
some simple way
like a tabular or linear representation.
And that's much harder design because
now you need someone who is not only
an expert and backgammon but also an
expert in reinforcement learning.
And you need a lot of intuition for
which features are good
This turned out to be very difficult in
practice and for a long time it was
extremely hard
to apply reinforcement learning methods
to complex problems.
Deep learning applies the same formula
to reinforcement learning that it did
to the computer mission problem which is
that we replace the manual feature
extraction
with automatically learned features
represented by a deep neural network
and train it end to end.
However in the reinforcement learning setting
typically for the breadth of problems
that we want to handle our intuition for
designing features
is substantially weaker than it is for
computer vision
and for this reason,
deep reinforcement learning methods have
a transformative effect on the
capabilities of reinforcement learning
algorithms.
So what does end-to-end learning mean
for sequential decision making?
Well, first let me explain what it means
to not have intended learning.
When you don't have intended learning
that means that you have to handle the
recognition part of the problem and the
control part of the problem separately.
So maybe you have one system that
figures out what you're seeing in an
image are you seeing a tiger or jaguar
or something innocuous and then a
pipeline that leads to another component
that decides what actually to take based
on that perceptual outcome.
And you train your perception system to
be a good perception system and
recognize
what you're seeing accurately and you
train your control system to be a good
control system to take the right actions.
But because the perception system is
trained separately it's not informed by
the demands
of the behavioral system it doesn't know
what kind of detections are important,
what kind are not important,
what kind of mistakes are costly
and what kind of mistakes are less costly.
And that's a big deal we
need to run away from the tiger.
An intense system closes the sensory
motor loop but actually trains the
entire system end-to-end
performing both perception and control
acquiring both visual
and behavioral features directly
informed by the final performance of the task.
Here's what that means in some example
application scenarios if you want to do
robotic control
a traditional robotics pipeline will
consist of stages
taking in observations estimating the
state such as the positions of objects
doing a little bit of modeling and prediction
figure out how those objects
will behave in the future
doing some planning based on that
modeling and prediction
doing some low level control on top of that
and so on
Importantly each stage in this
process can incur some error.
You could make a
mistake in detecting where the object is
at which point the plan you construct
might not have any meaningful effect in
the real world because it's based on
false premises.
An intent approach would overcome this
issue because
the each stage in this pipeline will be
informed by the demands of the next
stage down the line.
So you could imagine
a deepreinforcement learning
approach to robotic control
where you have
a convolutional deep neural network
that performs both perception and action.
So images from the robot's camera are
fitted to the bottom of this network
and outputs from the end are fed into
the robot's actuators.
This kind of sensory motor loop sort of
represents
a little microcosm of brain for this
robot with a little visual component a
little behavioral component.
But all of them are trained end-to-end
for the final performance of the task.
So you can think of the convolutional
layers to use a very strained analogy
as a kind of tiny highly specialized
visual cortex and the fully connected
layers is a tiny highly specialized
motor cortex.
But they're all trained and to end and
because of that they'll end up doing
whatever is optimal for the task
within the capabilities of their
representational capacity.
So then the robot could learn from
experience practicing this task
and using that to train all the weights
in this network end to end.
So if we think about these uh example
applications of reinforcement problems,
when we combine them with deep neural
network representations,
the reinforcement learning system really
represents
in a sense the entirety of the ai problem.
Supervised learning systems
require
input and output supervision.
Reinforced learning systems
aim for optimal behavior without relying
on such supervision just for
relying on reward feedback.
And deep models are what allows
reinforced learning algorithms to solve
complex problems end-to-end so
reinforcement learning
provides the mathematical formalism the
algorithmic foundations
while deep models provide the
representations that allow those
algorithmic foundations
to be scaled up to real-world systems.
So why should we study these questions now?
Well, there have been a number of
advances over the last decade that make
this a really exciting time to study
deep reinforcement learning.
First, there have been tremendous
advances in deep learning itself
methods for building
deep neural network representations.
There have also been a lot of advances
in reinforcement learning algorithms
that make it possible to scale these
methods up to use those deep learning
representations.
And lastly, advances in computational
capability
have made it more practical than ever before
to combine these two elements
That said the basic foundations of deep
reinforcement learning are not by any
means new.
For instance, there have been textbooks
on neural networks for control
going back decades going back to the
1980s.
And work even from the 90s has actually
discussed many of the
ingredients that are part of cutting
edge research today for instance this
phd thesis
from 1993 says a few things that modern
deep reinforcement learning researchers
would find very familiar such as,
reinforcement learning can be naturally
integrated with artificial neural
networks
to obtain high quality generalization.
Experience replays a simple technique
that implements this idea.
We'll learn about experience we play
later in the course.
Instructive training instances provided
by human teachers
can result in significant speed up.
That's uh we call that
curriculum learning or imitation learning,
hierarchical learning,
reinforced learning agents can
significantly reduce learning time by
hierarchical learning.
That's a cutting-edge research topic in
deep RL today.
And reinforced learning agents can deal
with a wide range of non-markovian
environments
by having a memory of their past and
we'll talk about integrating memory
and recurrence into deep learning
methods.
And of course these methods have had
enormous successes in the past too,
such as the td gammon system that i
mentioned before which was actually done
in 1996
more than 20 years prior to alphago
but in recent years we've seen some
pretty tremendous advances.
Deep reinforcement learning algorithms
that can directly learn to play video
games directly from raw image pixels
robotic systems that can learn a wide
range of highly generalizable skills
and deep reinforced learning algorithms
that could even beat the world champion
at go