hey everyone my name is kevin i'm one of
the gsis for this class and today i'll
be giving a lecture on pytorch and
neural networks
so at a high level the goal of this
class is pretty much to train an agent
to perform useful tasks
so this is what a typical training loop
might look like we start with some data
and we want to use that data to train a
model to determine how our agent is
going to act
and using that model we'll collect some
additional data and we'll keep repeating
that until we have something we're
satisfied with
so that model might be something like a policy
uh it could be a q function or
it could even be a dynamics model if
you're doing something like model based
url
and so that's going to be the area that
we focus on for today's lecture
the rest of the loop is not really
related to pytorch but you'll get some
experience with that in homework one two
so how do we train a model
typically you'll get some kind of
optimization problem like this so we
have some kind of loss function and we
want to minimize the loss on our
training data set
so there are a lot of different pieces
here we have a data set
we have some kind of
model probably a neural network that is
going to be making predictions
we have a loss function that defines how
well we're performing so far
and then we have some kind of
optimization algorithm that we use to
actually minimize the loss probably
gradient descent
and pytorch helps us do all these
things pretty much
so at a high level what pytorch does is
it's a python library that lets you
define neural networks and automatically
compute gradients for gradient descent
it definitely also lets you do a lot of
other things like for example work with
data sets switch out different
optimizers train and do inference on
gpus and stuff like that and we'll try
to cover some of these things in the
next few videos where we go through a
collab with some examples
so how does pytorch work um if you ever
used um any other deep learning library
for example tensorflow probably the big
difference the biggest difference is um
how pytorch computes gradients for
backprop(agaiton) everything else is pretty much
just a matter of knowing the names of
the different classes and functions if
you're transitioning to pytorch from
something else
but for backprop
what pytorch does is basically
let you define the forward pass the way
you'd normally write code
and you pretty much don't have to worry
about defining the backward pass at all
or any any kind of like computation graph
so this example uh what we do is we
define we're going to find three layers
each layer is going to be a linear
function followed by some non-linearity
so we have h1 h2 and then we have our
output y
so at this point that's pretty much all
you need to do
then if you want to do backprop you
basically choose some variable in this
case we'll choose the scalar y and we
want to take all the gradients with
respect to y so we just call y dot
backward
and what that's going to do is
pytorch is automatically going to
compute the gradients of y with respect
to each of your variables so y with
respect to w3 w2 and w1
and these gradients will be
automatically populated for your three
variables
yeah this is a super nice feature of
pytorch basically you can write your code
naturally as if you're just defining
functions that do some kind of
transformations on your input and you
don't have to worry about how the
backward pass is going to be computed
that's all taken care of for you
so in the next few videos we'll be going
over an interactive collab and we'll go
over some examples of how you can use
pytorch to train neural networks